Now let's look at the beginnings of what
led to modern mathematics and arithmetic,
with numbers, addition, multiplication,
subtraction.
I'm, I'm going to guess some kind of
division came in.
originally just addition and subtraction.
The best evidence we have about how ari,
remember that I mentioned counting goes
back thousands of years, maybe 35,000
BCE, maybe longer, using piles of pebbles
probably, certainly notches on bones,
probably notches on sticks.
And the notched bones have been found.
You have to interpret what they were used
for.
All sorts of theories out there, seasons
and phases of the moon, and things like
that.
My guess is the one that doesn't get
mentioned is probably the one that was
the most significant, which is probably
was the early monetary system.
And I say that because the first real
evidence we have for abstract numbers,
was money.
Why do we have numbers?
It was money folks.
You want to find new, you want to find
out where numbers came from, follow the
money[LAUGH].
go back to Sumeria and the fertile
crescent region what's now mainly Iraq,
and this was about 5,000 BCE.
it, it was period that began then, but,
but by 5,000 BCE is when we, we
definitely have artifacts that we are
pretty damn sure, we being the
anthropologists, not me.
What the anthropologists are pretty sure
that what happened then was the invention
of numbers and it was for monetary
purposes.
in other words, you need numbers to have
money.
Because num, money comes in numerical
quantities.
One of these, one of those, one of those,
ten of these.
the interesting thing is you didn't have
numbers until you needed money, so the
driving force was mediating human
transactions of goods.
[COUGH] And the essential reason why
numbers came on was banking.
Okay, it was essentially the invention of
banking.
It was the first bankers.
Bankers were the people essentially who
applied money as mediating quantities in
trade.
interesting how that has changed, I mean
bankers now apply banking to figments of
the imagination.
>> [LAUGH].
>> But back then, it was too yeah.
Back then it was to actual physical
goods.
But not quite.
The vote set in immediately, because
immediately you introduce money, you've
got something fictitious whose value
depends purely on, on human agreement.
Okay, here was the evidence, and it was
discovered in Iraq by Denise
Schmandt-Besserat, who I think is now
professor Emeritus at the University of
Texas at Austin.
She was here on the Sloan Center on the
hill for a year many years ago.
but now she was a young anthropologist
going out into the fertile crescent
region.
And all over the place she kept finding
these burial sites and these, these ruins
of homes and things in which there were
piles of clay tokens.
Sometimes grouped together in, in ways
that suggested some kind of an order.
And they were different shapes.
some of them looked, recognize but that
looks like it might be an oil jar, it
looks like it could be a goose.
some of them, one of them somewhere looks
as it could be a mill for grinding corn
or something.
Some of that looks[INAUDIBLE] some kind
of a pepper corn.
So these look as though they might have
been tokens.
For things that people would trade.
Jars of oils, bales of hay, geese, oxen,
loaves of bread, and so forth.
So, the suspicion was, that these were
probably tokens to represent your goods.
If you had 5 geese to sell, you maybe had
5 of these tokens to represent them.
So the, the supposition was, and this is
a reasonable supposition because the
Sumerian society was pretty complex.
It was getting to be like a modern
society.
There was structure in, in the society.
You know, this was the drive, this was
one of the centers of modern civilization
coming along.
And so the supposition she made was that
these were tokens that represented goods.
Okay.
And here are some of them and so if you
wanted to trade things you wouldn't
necessarily have to worry, you would, you
have so many sheep and things but may be
the sheep be in the field but you have
tokens that represented the sheep.
So you would instead, so when you sh, you
trade, you would swap your tokens for
somebody else's oxen tokens, and then the
goods would eventually trade.
And so the tokens you had in your hand
represented the things you owned.
That was your bank account, and it was a
collection of tokens.
Not unlike a pocketful of change, huh?
Those were the tokens, except there were
different tokens for the different
objects with different shapes.
Okay, so the next thing you need is a way
of keeping your tokens secure because
that was a measure of your worth.
And so bankers came along to look after
your tokens for you, and what they would
do is you would go along with it, and now
we're just, I'm telling you the story
that the anthropologists came up with to
explain what was going on.
The, you came, you went, you had your
tokens, the banks kept your tokens, they
would take a sheet of wet clay, put your
tokens in the clay, fold it up, and seal
it, bake it in the sun, and there was
your secure bank account.
All nice and secure, locked away.
Okay.
Now the problem was, of course, if you
want to trade, you had to break open the
thing.
Take out the things, change them, and
reseal it.
Good business to be in banking.
Constant need for bankers to break open
the shells and reseal them and put their
stamp on them, okay.
So already the bankers were there hanging
on, taking our money in the process.
There's 10% or whatever they would take,
so then,
Some entrepreneurial person came along
and said, you know, it's fine if we crack
open the thing when we're actually doing
a trade.
But if I'm just making a bid on
something, I don't want to pay the banker
to break this apart and put it together.
If I want to just show my worth, why
don't I before you seal up this thing
take the tokens and press them on the
outside, then put them in and seal it.
So on the outside of the, of the, of the
sealed envelope, the clay envelope you've
got tokens, indentations of the tokens so
you don't have to break it open to see
how many tokens there are.
You just need to look at the
indentations.
That's an advance, okay?
Your worth, so if you, interesting areas
of structuring.
We've now got real sheep and real geese,
and real jars of oil represented by
artifacts, tokens.
Tokens are then put into a clay envelope
and the tokens are now represented by
marks on the outside.
We're about to invent writing.
Writing by the, for those people who like
to think that mathematics is supreme, as
far as we know, writing numbers came
before writing words.
Right, it all began with numbers, and it
was all about money.
So, they put these tokens out, so you've
got abstract markers, symbols,
representing the token, the tokens
represent the objects.
So, you're already two steps removed from
the real world, and you've got these,
these tokens.
And that was fine for a while, and then
after, you know, and then 1,000 years
goes by, and then another entrepreneurial
person comes along and says, you know?
We don't really need those tokens inside,
all you need is 1 token for each kind of
object.
Because you can use the same, same jar of
oil token, three times, if you've got 3
jar's of oil.
So you just need different tokens to make
these indentations.
But it doesn't matter where these tokens
are.
It's really about the indentations.
The tokens don't matter their just like
the golden fort knox you know, you and I
don't swap the golden fort knox it's just
there alright, you just go with the
tokens.
So, when you do that you can think well
in that case I don't really need a clay
envelope I can just have a tablet.
With marks on it, and here is one of the
tablets.
So these came later, flat tablets with
the different indentations representing
in different areas.
You know, there would be different things
they're representing.
it could well be that the stock of the
tokens in different boxes represented
different kinds of things.
This was presumably some code, but it got
sophisticated and we have abstract
markings on a piece of clay that
represents your net worth.
And if that doesn't look familiar, it
ought to.
>> [LAUGH].
>> 5,000 BCE, we got credit cards,[LAUGH]
made out of clay.
Okay okay.
That according to the anthropologists.
This has been sort of, this is pretty
well accepted in, in the business.
Their business, not my business.
I'm, I'm, I'm happy with this.
It seems like a good explanation is where
we, we have money.
Certainly, numbers came out of that area.
And this, this, this seems the most
plausible explanation given the available
evidence.
Okay so that's where we get counting
numbers, it was for money.
But there was another system of numbers.
What about the numbers that are used for
building pyramids, measuring volumes of
things seeing how much land you owe, you
own when the Nile delta, this is the Nile
Delta.
When the Nile Delta floods and you have
to remap the thing?
there was measurement.
That was going on as well.
And one of the interesting things about
this is to, to modern eyes, those are
both systems of numbers.
Those give you the natural numbers.
And that gives you what we call the real
numbers.
This is a 19th century, eh, the 1930,
20th century interpretation.
These were not thought as numbers.
They were quantities, lengths, volumes,
interestingly not areas.
Areas seem to be cognitively complicated.
But lengths, and volumes and quantities,
so these were regarded as essentially
separate.
The Greeks tried to combine them, and
when they discovered that you couldn't,
the famous discovery that the square root
of 2 was irrational, they pushed them
apart again, and, and they took that as
meaning that you can't marry, marry these
with those because of what they call the
incommensurables.
You simply couldn't use whole numbers to
capture this.
Only at the end of the 19th century, 2000
years later, were mathematicians finally
able to marry these things together, in a
single number system called the real
numbers.
That's very, very recent, and this is
part of why mathematics got interested in
concepts and relationships because these
guys took a lot of of building.
But the reason it took a lot of building
was cause of these were regarded as
foundational, and yet these, from a
cognitive point of view, these are both
basic.
Human beings have a cognition about
quantities, discrete quantities.
We, we can count things.
We also have sense of lengths and
volumes.
We have a sense of continuous size.
So the human cognitive system captures
both and it just took mathematics a long
time to marry those in a single system.
If you read, read Newton's Principia
where he talks about the calculus.
He's not talking about numbers, he's
talking about quantities.
Calculus in Newton's terms.
Calculus wasn't applied to numbers, it
was applied to lengths and distances.
we interpret it today in term's of
numbers, but that's because we have a
different conception of numbers.
>> [MUSIC] Stanford University.