Now here, and this also goes for, for
most of Europe, western Europe at least
certainly for these countries that are
essentially capitalist.
we build our number system on commerce
and trade.
Okay, we start with counting numbers and
elementary arithmetic.
And this is typically how we teach kids
in, in arithmetic.
Then we proceed to fractions, then we
introduce negative numbers as best you
can, it's tricky that one.
Smart kids ask questions that are very
difficult to answer.
then we slip in real numbers under the
heading algebra, we just, we pretend
there's not a problem there.
And from the point of view of a teacher
the first step is pretty good, there were
good metaphors for counting, I mean, you
list all you can't count.
You can think of all sorts of metaphors
for dealing with positive numbers.
fractions is pretty good, you can talk
about breaking things away, I mean you
know, American mathematics book are
talking about pizzas, but I guess that
reflects just American diet.
European text books we, we cut up
straight lines, and squares, and
rectangles, and pies, actually we don't
cut up pizzas in Europe, we cut up pies.
Which is misleading, because pie tends to
mean something else, but anyway.
but there are good metaphors about
sharing out infractions.
maybe the numbers are sort of, you, you
read all sorts of weird stuff about,
helium balloons on balances, and things.
which is a really weak and misleading
metaphor, but anyway, there's, there's
also some problems here, and and kids
sort of get lost.
And, many in[UNKNOWN] has enormous
trouble really knowing what negative
numbers are, you know, minus times minus
equals plus the reason why we won't
discuss.
[LAUGH] it was, it was[UNKNOWN] I think
it was.
[NOISE] And in fact, most people actually
can't give a good explanation of why
minus one times minus one is plus one.
And it's not 'cuz they're stupid, it's
because it's actually kind of a tricky
thing to do.
and this one, this is the famous don't
ask, don't tell policy.
You just don't raise the issue, you just
say, well, there's no problem here, we
just have these continuous lines.
and, and then students get to university,
and they look at the construction of the
real numbers from the rational numbers
they think,[SOUND] I'm not going to be a
mathematician.
[COUGH] OK and that's more or less a
historical thread, starting in Sumeria
and going through sort of commerce driven
society.
In fact, the rest of today's lecture is
going to be about how it came.
The Western Europe and then the United
States was the dominant economic power
for many centuries.
Why is the word banking from an Italian
word, why is the word policy from an
Italian word, why is double entry book
keeping coming out of Italy.
Why are financial districts often called
long bad street, why is all of the
terminology about banking and finance and
insurance and international trip, why is
so much of that Italian?
I'll come to that in the second half of
the lecture.
That was a case where mathematics really
drove modern society and gave dominance
to first Italy and then Germany, then
Western Europe and then Unites States.
And just took over from the rest of the
world in economics.
And with it, science as well.
Why is it that Galileo was in Pisa?
Just it, why did it all happen in Italy?
Something happened there.
Well, several things happened, but, one
of them was to do with the, with this
sequence of learning.
But there's another way you could learn
about[INAUDIBLE] , the[UNKNOWN]
educational system.
And this one was developed in the Soviet
Union.
I'm not sure if it's still used very much
in Russia,[COUGH] .
this is known as the, the Davydov
curriculum.
who was a Russian psychologist and
educator.
Died not, not that long ago, Vasily
Davydov.
And he said we should start with the, you
see, the problem with that last picture
was going from the rationals, what, the,
the negative numbers is a problem, but
going to the real numbers is a real
problem.
You've got the don't ask, don't tell
policy.
It's really very difficult conceptually,
and he said, we've got a concept of, of
measurement, that predates, by hundreds
of thousands of years, counting, namely,
measurements of lengths and things.
Most creatures have a sense of distance
and length.
They use it to sort of catch prey, to
swing from tree to tree, I mean, there's
an innate sense of distance, in many
creatures, much more sophisticated than a
sense of con, of con, of counting.
Counting is, discreet counting is much
more restrictive in the, in the animal
world.
Okay, so, most creatures, including
humans, have this very rich sense of, of
quantative measurement.
He said we should build our number system
and, we should begin with the real
numbers, and with algebra, and then
arithmetic will drop out as a special
case, which is true.
because when you have the real numbers,
the natural numbers are just points on a
line, and it's just a particular instance
of these things.
So he said it's better to begin with this
rich sense of distance and volume that we
had for a millennia.
[COUGH] and in building a curriculum he
took Vygotsky's ideas and talked about
spontaneous concepts by scientific
concepts and these are all technical
terms, which I won't go into details
about but we can chat about them offline
sometime.
Spontaneous concepts, when children just
abstract from everyday experiences.
But human beings don't just abstract,
they theorize.
And they can theorize from a very early
age, and in fact they do, I mean, very
young children theorize a lot of things.
They form theories at a very early age.
And he says with a bit of, with a bit of
nudging, you can take those ideas, of the
theorizing capacity and develop what he
calls scientific concepts.
And this allows you to build a curriculum
in which you get very naturally, at a
very early age, from the age of something
like six to eight.
You can begin by doing algebra and
solving equations, and then arithmetic
follows special cases.
If you are interested, I have a, an
online column called Devling's Angle that
the MEA.
If you just type Devling's Angle and you
go back to 2008, 2009, Christmas around
2008, 2007.
I actually had two articles on these.
it's actually hard to find much about
this.
This is written about a lot in the
educational research literature.
my two articles are almost the only
articles I've seen and come across that
tries to explain these things to a
general audience.
But there's another way, and so these
different cognitions can be taken
advantage of for educational purposes.
[MUSIC]
Stanford University.