[BLANK_AUDIO].
>> Yes.
>> What is the difference between an
algebraic expression, an algorithm and a
model?
>> The difference between algebraic, what?
>> Expression.
>> Expression, an algorithm and a model.
>> And a model?
Okay, well the word model is It's usually
not, a lot of things in mathematics.
It's very often just means an equation or
a set of equations where you take some
feature of the world, something going on
in the world and you represent it by a
model.
You know, it could be a graphic, it could
be a network, whatever it is, it's some
arithmetic, some algebraic, some
mathematical representation of something
in the world that you can solve.
So you're modelling the world so these
abstractions, in the course of building a
model when you apply that model to the
world, then very often, lead you to or
involves developing algorithms.
Algorithms are procedures for solving
problems.
Let me back up, I think them the crucial
distinction is that the model is a
representation of an aspect of the world.
An algorithm is a procedure for doing
things that allow you to make conclusions
about the world.
Very often an algorithm of wise is in a
used in the context of a model.
In fact arguably always this.
You need a model that represents
something in the world, and in that model
you can apply algorithms to draw
conclusions about the world.
relative to that model, you can also do
algebraic reasoning, which may or may not
be algorithmic.
Algorithmic means step one, step two,
step three, step four, but not all
mathematical reasoning is algorithmic.
It can be just, i've no idea how to solve
it, i've no idea how to solve it, i've no
idea how to solve it, oh, I can solve it
that way.
It's insight, it's the ah-hah moment, and
a lot of mathematics is like that.
It's very much not algorithmic.
often, mathematics preceeds by, no idea,
no idea, no idea, oh, great idea.
And then when you reflect on that idea
you can get an algorithm so that all the
people can do it.
okay.
So a classic example I guess would be
solving the quadratic.
It was a great idea, you can do it by
turning it into a perfect square,
completing the square and ancient method
we all learn in high school or in middle
school.
And the first person who did that you
know that's brilliant, we just say, wow,
I just turn this into a real square, now
actually, you could imagine that
happening if you're thinking
geometrically actually.
But the moment that person did that, you
can turn it into the formula for the
quadratic.
And then you just got an algorithm, you
just plug in the values, x is minus b
plus or minus the square root of b
squared minus 4ac over 2a.
There's the algorithm, that's the
procedure.
That came about as a result of a greater
how moment.
So, back to the question, models of how
we start with the world, and represent
them in mathematics, and then once we've
got a model, once we've got the world
captured, an aspect of the world captured
in mathematics, we can apply algorithms,
step by step procedures or we can apply
algebraic reasoning or geometric
reasoning to draw conclusions about the
world.
And that reasoning may be algorithmic or
it may just be thinking relationally
until you have an insight.
Okay, I think I've got as close as I'm
going to get on the spur of the moment,
yeah.
>> [MUSIC]
Stanford University.