>> There was an article several weeks ago or
a month ago in the New York Times about
the great disservice done to our
educational system by requiring high
school students to.
>> Oh, Hacker, that guy Hacker, yes.
Can you comment on that[CROSSTALK]?
>> I already have in public, but[LAUGH] I
could do it again.
couple of things.
If his article was about, the great
disservice that's done to our kids by
teaching them what we currently teach
them in their high school algebra class,
I'm 100% on his side.
But he didn't.
He said, we shouldn't be teaching
algebra.
What he should have said is, we need to
teach algebra, instead of that excuse
that's taught in the schools for algebra.
Yeah?
I hope you're recording me, so[LAUGH] I'm
going to get slaughtered by this.
No It, it's, what's taught is not
algebra.
If you go back and look at what
Al-Khwarizmi was talking about and say,
this is algebra.
This is clearly important.
This is clearly powerful.
This is valuable stuff, and you teach it
in the context.
Then it makes sense and everyone can see
the use of it.
I guarantee, that the person who wrote
that, and probably almost all students In
the course of their everyday life or
their recreational activities, use Excel
spreadsheets to do things.
Excel is an implementation in silicon of
algebra.
That's what it is.
It's a, a spreadsheet is modern algebra.
A modern implementation of algebra.
So anyone who could, was, keeps track of
sports scores, or runs, runs events, or
keeps track of their finances using a
spreadsheet, they are using algebra right
there and then.
So Hocka was saying, we don't need
spreadsheets, and you don't need to know
about them.
That's what he was actually saying, but
he didn't realize that.
So, it's a matter of what he was getting
at and he missed the point but if it was
a matter of what's taught that's a
different issue.
>> So, I mean I don't use spreadsheets that
much but they seem more arithmetical than
algebraic.
>> Yeah in terms of the.
No but.
That's right because the issue is and
this is really why.
it, it was sort of implicit in what the
the, the traders were doing in 89th
century, in, in the Muslim empire when
they were doing the trading.
What they're saying is, there were
calculations which you have to apply
again and again and again, and the
numbers change.
If you're trading, you're multiplying by
an exchange rate, you're doing something,
you're doing this, and it's the same
calculation essentially, but the numbers
change.
So if you have a method that tells you
how to do it for any numbers whatsoever,
you're at the level of algebra.
And then the spreadsheets, that's what
spreadsheets do.
The do arithmetic efficiently, so that
you just change the numbers and then you
just, literally now, you just sort of
pull the cursor down and it does the same
calculation for all of them.
So it's doing algebra but still the
algebra in the sense of[INAUDIBLE]
because it is applied to numbers.
The focus is on calculation but it's
general methods for solving problems that
are all essentially alike and once you
looking attempt to general methods your
level of algebra, which is why when I
solved about Babylonians I said this is
really algebra.
They were writing down a formula, they
were writing down instructions for
dealing with specific numbers but the way
they were writing it, was saying take any
number and do this and this and this and
the moment you start seeing take any
number your essentially doing algebra.
Fortunately the guy that worked in the
New York Times know that you know this.
I tend to avoid writing about something,
publicly, that I don't really
understand[LAUGH].
And, I think he overstepped the lines
there.
But if he'd said, what my kids are
learning in the algebra class, hey, I'm
on his side.
But I think that means we should reform
what's going on in the algebra class.
>> [MUSIC]
Stanford University.