>> Okay, yes.
>> derivatives be a combination or use of
algorithms?
>> You mean in, in the terms of calculus?
>> [INAUDIBLE].
>> Oh, actually I, one of the things I, I
probably will do is do a half a session
on calculus.
Because calculus is the, is the modern
technology well, without calculus we
wouldn't have modern technology.
And calculus so I'm going to differ with
detailed answer so I will definitely now
next week, if I'm going to talk about
next week is calculus.
Because it needs, it needs more than a
quick answer but let me give you a quick
answer any way because I'm on a roll now.
Okay,
The brilliance of calculus and its
absolutely brilliant is, it takes
something and its, its almost the same
brilliance as algebra.
in that sort of take something that's
intrinsically difficult in that case,
tedious because you're doing the same
calculation many times and by[INAUDIBLE]
up the abstraction instead of having to
do the same calculation many times, you
have a general method, a formula that you
can just apply without thinking.
That's what calculus, calculus takes an
incredibly difficult problem involving
rates of continuous change which when you
analyze it involves talking about
infinitesimal increments, and things
changing of infinitesimal amounts of time
gets very deep both philosophically and
computationally in terms of[UNKNOWN]
conceptually Philosophically and
conceptually difficult because you're
dealing with these infinitely,
infinitesimally small things and so
forth.
Okay.
Very challenging, very, very difficult.
In the seventeenth century it was a major
headache for people to do it.
Archimedes had struggled with it
thousands of years earlier, got results
but it was very hard to understand
exactly what it meant, how to make sense
of it.
What calculus does is take something
extremely difficult, and turning it into
a mindless algorithm.
Calculus is just a set of syntactic
rules, that allow you to work out the
answers to things involving continuous
change.
It took it from one end of the spectrum
to the other.
Calculus starts with something that is
conceptually intellectual, unbelievably
challenging.
The infinite is something that the human
mind literally can't grasp, and yet it
rears its head as soon as you start
looking at infinitesimal changes in
continuity.
It takes that extremely deep stuff that
our minds can't fully wrap around, and
reduces it to a completely mindless set
of symbolic manipulation.
That is technology written large.
Take something complicated and would use
it to something just push buttons.
Calculus was one of the World's first
great conceptual technology.
Technology in a sense that it's a black
box, you plug something in and the answer
comes out.
Magic happens inside, Magic happens
inside Calculus.
I became a mathematician when I met
Calculus in my last year of high school.
I thought Calculus, I thought mathematics
was kinda[UNKNOWN], I was going to be a,
I was going to go to university
Physicist, I wanted to do Physics.
I went to high school when Sputnick went
up.
I mean I thought space exploration all
this stuff so, so I went to univ, I was
going to go to university to do physics.
Spent all my time doing physics, wasn't
particularly good at mathematics.
Well, that's not true.
I, I wasn't gifted at mathematics, but I
needed to do it for physics, so I put a
lot of effort into any mathematics, which
I viewed as a set of tools that would
help me in physics.
Then in after my first year of sixth form
when I'm sort of 17, getting into the
last year of high school.
We start doing calculus.
We started really doing calculus.
I mean just looking at what the
definition of the derivative and so
forth.
And I'm presented with this stuff that A,
is obviously very powerful.
It allows you to calculate you know,
where the moon's going to be 3 weeks from
now.
It allows you to calculate all these
other things.
It's going to, it allows you to calculate
what's going to happen to a spinning top
when it starts to slow down.
It allows you to calculate all of these
wonderful predictive things with
incredible accuracy, and yet I have no
idea how it worked.
And for me to have something that was
thrust upon me that was clearly powerful,
and worked, and in a sense was simple
because you know you look that, a couple
of pages of the textbooks that is how it
works.
Make no sense to me.
And I'm that kind of guy who wants to
lift the hood up and see what's going on
here.
so for me, what turned me into a
mathematician, was realizing that there
was something powerful that I didn't
understand.
And it took me many years to understand
it, and by the time I did, I was a
mathematician.
because once you've got it, it was funny,
because most of the other kids in the
class, and, and at the beginning, my
teacher, said look.
Here's the formula, if you differentiate
x to the n, you get nx to the n minus 1.
Just use the sucker, and get the problem
solved.
And I was that kid that kept saying, yeah
okay, but where did that formula come
from, why does that formula work?
And I was the only kid in the class,
including the teacher, actually, who
really worried about why that was the
case.
you know, that was clear, that was the
point where I became a mathemetician.
Because everybone else was content to
just use it and get the answer.
And for me, the fact that they could that
without understanding it, is what made it
interesting.
because I wanted to know what Newton was
thinking when he came up with that thing
or what[UNKNOWN] was thinking.
So I'll come back to that next week.
It's really good question and it's a big
answer and it's the that our modern, and
we're doing big themes.
We've already looked at numbers.
What's the biggest invention that
mathematicians have produced that changed
the world?
Hindu arabic numerals.
That's fundamental to modern life for
everybody.
So that was the biggest one I would say.
What's the next biggest one?
Probably algebra, which is more efficient
ways of dealing with numbers.
And the next one's going to be calculus
because that gives us, because the first
one gives us all our commerce in our
financial business, in our, you know,
quantative stuff, money, began with
money, as far as we know.
All of that comes on from the numbers,
and on the other side we've got calculus,
that gives us all our modern science and
technology.
So these are big, big themes.
okay.
That was slightly more than a little
digression, but I'll come back to
calculus next time.
Okay, shall we take a break now?
Let's take a break now and then we'll
come back, and we'll talk about how we
[INAUDIBLE] count the votes in an
election.
[MUSIC]
.
>> Stanford University.