Welcome back, and there's two topics
tonight, the first is the one I began in
just sort of got into a little bit at the
beginning, at the end of last time.
And so, I'll pick up on that, actually
think about the birth of algebra.
Which is part of a general sort of
historical theme that's going to be
running through this.
But I'm also into sparsing it with sort
of more up to date things, and given the
events in the political arena, the second
half is going to be about how do we count
the votes in a general election.
Okay?
And the spoiler is you tell me who you
want to win and I can give you a fair way
to count the votes so that person will
win.
>> [INAUDIBLE] [LAUGH] .
>> Okay?
So, you know?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> It's, it's not who wins, well actually,
it could be who wins the debate that can
really get into the White House, but
really the game is won or lost when you
decide how you're going to count the
votes.
So that would be the second half.
Okay, I'll go a little bit, I'll go
fairly quickly for the first couple of
minutes, because we, we got into this
last time, and this is about the birth of
algebra.
And I pointed out that we need to be
careful what we mean by algebra.
In fact, even today, there were two
meanings.
There's what I'd called sophisticated, or
aritmatical thinking, or meta
arithmetical thinking, which is the, the
kind of, which is what most people think
of as algebra.
It's what's the basis of algebra in the
high school system.
And then there's what mathematicians call
algebra, sometimes known as higher
algebra.
[COUGH] Okay.
Well first of all, and, and the focus
mainly is going to be almost exclusively
is on the former, which is algebra as it
arose out of arithmetic as a, as a way of
improving arithmetic calculations.
So I'm not going to be touching on higher
algebra, [SOUND] which is what is done,
so if you say that, if you come, if you
go around the, if you go around the
Stanford campus, you're going to math
department, and you go into an office and
someone says this is professor X, and
professor X is an algebraist, this is not
what professor X does.
Professor X does something very
different.
Perhaps works on something like Fermat's
last theoroem.
Although that turned out not to be
algebraic in the end, but that's another
story.
Okay, certainly not algebra, because it
uses symbols.
In fact, algebra, for many years, was
written, in a non symbolic fashion.
It was always done symbolically.
by the way, I will mention that, if you
start going on the web, and you go to,
even to Wikipedia and you look for
accounts on algebra, there's a lot of
misinformation floating out there.
That's one of the, Wikipedia's actually
pretty good on a lot of mathematical
content, but the last time I looked, in
terms of the history of algebra, it was
really very weak.
Largely, because it was based on the few
textbooks that were available, that
people have access to, most of which are
actually quite old, and scholarship has,
has advanced quite a bit since then.
[COUGH] Okay, so this is one of those
instances where beware of what you find
on the web.
Okay, we certainly so, it, it's not
because it's symbolic that makes it
arguable, it's the kind of thinking
that's going on.
[COUGH] and in fact the symbolic part
although you can trace it back to these
fairly early origins it really wasn't
until, even later than the 13th century,
that that we get modern symbolic algebra.
In fact 16 centuries when you can first
really identify the work of Phan's Viete,
Viete you can really recognize symbolic
algebra in the modern sense.
Okay, so, the key distinction is it's a
logical thinking rather than numerical
quantity thinking.
it's not calculating with numbers, it's
reasoning logically about numbers.
so whereas arithmetic is definitely
quantitative, algebra is very much a
qualitative discipline.
But it's focused on numbers, this kind of
algebra is still focused on numbers.
And one of the ways to distinguish it is
where was in calculation, you have some
data, and you do things to that data to
get an answer.
You can't get it with the data, you add
numbers together, you multiply them, and
it's a forward looking thing where you're
combining things.
You're, you're literally not getting new
information, you're combining information
you've got.
In order to get a result that was already
implicit in that data.
one of the features of algebra, is it's a
little bit different.
You know that there's an answer out
there, you give it a name, and then you
sort of almost work backwards.
You reason what, would have to happen to
get to that thing.
So you reason, logically, in order to, to
determine that value.
now it doesn't matter whether you call
that unknown by a name, and in fact in
medieval mathematics, it was used by
terms that really meant the thing.
You do this to the thing, you do that to
the thing and then you find out that the
thing is this.
so there were various terms in Latin and
other languages which really translate as
the thing.
and it only became known as the x,
solving for x, was more like 16, 17th
century.
So it's not to do with the language.
And, you know, my knowledge with, with
music, music is transcends the musical
notation, and algebra transcends any
particular notation.
It's the way of thinking that that
distinguishes it.
[COUGH] So my, one of the things I
mentioned last time was that, taking a
formula and putting numbers in is
outright arithmetic but the deriving of
that formula in the first place usually
involves qualitative, what we might call
algebraic reasoning.
And the examples I gave, again, last time
very quickly was solving a quadratic by
guessing and calculation.
That just doing arithmetic, you make a
guess and then you do some calculation.
If you're systematic and you substitute
in a formula, that's also arithmetic.
But if you look at the the method whereby
the formula itself is obtained.
Or in the case of a particular example
like this, looking at the structure of it
and reasoning about it then that's
really, I mean there's a, there's a fuzzy
borderline, and some people might
disagree with [UNKNOWN] classifying this
as algebraic because it is a fuzzy
borderline.
But I would say when you start doing
this, you've really crossed over into
into algebraic thinking, lets say its
fuzzy and and you know different people
might want to put the borderline in a
different place.
So I would say that's, that's, that's
that's moved over and that's, that's,
that's really algebra.