And when we look back historically with
the benefit of hindsight, we can see
algebraic thinking going back a long way.
It certainly wasn't symbolic algebra in
the sense we have now, although let me
nuance that, 'cause I've already referred
to that implicitly.
There's two issues.
There's how did they record what they
were doing, how did they write down on
their tablets and whatever, their
parchment.
How did they write down algebra?
Or arithmetic, for that matter?
And then the other issue is, how did they
do it?
Well, they've always, it's always been
done symbolically.
It's hard to imagine how you can do it
without some kind of scratching of some
sort of abstract symbols.
But when they wrote it down for many
centuries it was written down in words.
And I, I eluded to that last week in
connection with, with the Leonardo
Fibonacci although maybe it was two weeks
ago.
The when before the printing press when
thins were written down they had to
written down in a manner that allowed
fairly reliable copying.
And the writers knew that the scribes
would be literary people that could
probably get the words right, but they
wouldn't necessarily understand the
symbols.
And you know, one matter, one symbol
that's written wrongly can turn a correct
result into an incorrect result, can turn
something sensible into gibberish.
So in order to be to give some guarantee
that results will be preserved when when
things are copied.
most things are written in words and but
the, but it was always done symbolically.
So and one of the things you find on, on
some websites is a distinction between
rhetorical algebra and symbolic algebra.
That's, that's, that's all missing the
point.
It wasn't that it was a different kind of
algebra, it was just the distinction
between how it was written and how it was
done.
[COUGH] .
so we got the evidence of the Babylonians
doing something that was essentially
algebra.
it was, it was very much calc in term of
geometric problems.
but some of these, in some way was very
practical.
Some of them were actually numerical
problems that were couched in algebra in
geometric terms.
And some just seemed to be recreational.
[COUGH] and even though they didn't have
notational devices for talking about
variables in general cases, they talked
in terms of specific numbers.
It was clear, just as we do with modern
recipes very often, you know, take two
cups of this and three cups of that.
And you just as-, assume you can double
or triple any of the units.
it was clear that they applied in
general.
But it was with hindsight, this was
algebraic thinking.
okay and indeed to the degree of having
an unknown, an unknown that you reason
about.
the unknown wasn't a li-, wasn't a
number, it was with geometrics or the
unknown was a line.
That's algebra.
We might want to call it geometric
algebra, just to clear about it but again
this is a modern term.
They were just doing their stuff.
they were just trying to solve problems
and then in some cases, just to have a
good time.
and as mentioned a moment ago.
Sometimes they would do this to solve
arithmetic problems.
That, that's a feature that we can see
later on in the work of Omar Khayyam and
so forth, that it was a geometric
approach to essentially numeric problems.
[COUGH] And here's one, I think I got as
far as this last time this problem which
I've translated from base-60 into modern
decimal notation.
And it's written in, in words.
I added the second, the area of my two
squares, and I put it in decimal
notation, and expressed the problem, and
then it gave a geometric solution of
procedure, an algorthm if you like, an
algorithm for solving it.
in modern terms I expressed the area of
my two squares x squared plus y squared,
and the area, I did them together, is, it
comes up, is 1525, and then another
condition gives me that equation.
So I got two equations, one quadratic,
one linear, and you have to solve them.
That's pretty sophisticated.
it's pretty sophisticated in symbols but
if you're thinking about it
geometrically, I think most people today
[COUGH] though we could easily solve that
using algebraic pr-, procedures.
geometrically that's I would find that a
bit of a challenge geometrically.
this kind of problem was solved all over
the place.
You, you get the Egyptians doing it in
the rhind papyrus Chinese, these are
famous works from history.
And the early Greeks in Euclid's elements
but in those cases it's, it would fall, I
would say, and most historians I've
consulted which is not a lot.
But I've at least consulted modern
historians would say that that's not
really algebraic.
yeah, I should, I'm drawing on so, when I
wrote my book on Fibonacci the man of
numbers, I consulted with three of the
leading scholars, one Italian and two
American, on Medieval period.
Actually the, the, the pre-Medieval
period, the sort of the, the
Arabic-Persian Period in the 8th, 9th
centuries.
And and then they, the medieval period
and this, I consulted with three of the
best modern scholars on those areas, and
I'm, I'm pulling on those guys for my
information.
Rather than none of them have written,
books actually that's not quite true.
one of them's written some books but not,
none of the three have really written a
lot about what they know.
Not in the form of a book.
So their, their knowledge hasn't really
filtered on to the onto the internet,
yet.
Okay.
And I think, yes, I think it would get as
far as this.
Whereas we would do a plus b squared is a
squared plus 2a plus b squared, the
Greeks and others would think of that
geometrically in terms of actual areas.
You know, we talk about x squared but at
the, the word square indicates that its a
square floating around.
So a plus b squared that means its a
square which transfer a plus b and you
find that kind of thing, this kind of
geometric reasoning rather than algebraic
reasoning in all of those famous works.
Then we get something that really is
beginning to look like modern algebra
absent the x's and the y's and the z's,
which were not going to come till the
16th century.
And this is Diophantus who wrote this
multi-volume book, Arithmetica.
The word arithmetic is actually in the
title.
But this is really arithmetic done from a
higher order perspective.
it really was algebraic thinking.
we can recognize it as algebra.
Absent the symbols we can reco-, and
there are, there are symbols, but they're
not the, the familiar modern x, y's, and
z's and so forth.
but it was definite introducing an a, an
unknown, and then reasoning logical
solving equations and that was around
152, 150 Current Era.
so there were these letters, but that's,
you know, it's not symbolic algebra in
the modern sense, but it certainly is
algebra.
negative numbers we use, and he used
these techniques that we'll see in a
moment restoration and confrontation
moving things from one side of an
equation to another, eliminating like
terms from both sides.
And solved, use, used these methods to
solve polynomials up to degree six.
Okay, now let's, I don't think I got as
far as this.
I think this is where I stopped last
time.
Okay, so the, if we want to trace the
historical thread now, beyond Deophantus,
then we'll go into India, Brahmagupta
around 600 Common Era.
And he wrote this book which I am not
even going to attempt to pronounce But it
roughly means something like correctly
established teachings of Brahma.
that's to some disagreement exactly when
zero appeared.
But this is one of the, certainly one of
the first clear appearances of zero,
meaning that's there a discussion of the
properties of zero.
I know that you add zero to anything you
don't change it.
You multiply by zero, you get zero.
But that kind of a discussion, very
recognizable algebra.
We gain absent more than x, y and z.
Gloss.
And then solutions of quadratic formula,
including zero and negative numbers.
So that's very well established.
along 6, 600 or so of current year .
Then the next huge step, and this is that
path that I alluded to in connection with
and actually where you begin down in
India with the Hindu Arabic numerals.
Then, the, the, the Arabic speaking,
Persian speaking traders moving that up
Towards North Africa, and then crossing
the Mediterranean to Italy, and sort of a
three seminal figures from a historical
perspective.
There's Brahmagupta and then there's
al-Khwarizmi, and then there's Leonardo,
you know.
They, they were just three, and, and
essentially what they did that was
distinct was they each wrote a book that
survived.
if you want to change things, you can
write, you can do all sorts of things but
if you want to have a major effect on
history it will be recognized writing a
big book is, is of in a good way.
we know you regard Euclid, is been the
guy who arbitrated geometry.
Its not clear that Euclid did any of the
work with the origi-, they originated any
of the work in his book, he probably did.
But the real power for Euclid's elements
is the way it was organized, made
systematic, and made available to us and
laid out in a nice way.
and the same was true with al-Khwarizmi,
what two very important books, and
likewise with Leonardo.
You clearly have to be very good to do
that, but you, a lot of the work is
collection.
You know, that's why I ended up comparing
Leonardo to Steve Jobs.
He just make a really good job of
collecting it and marketing it and making
it accessible and that's how to influence
the world.