Okay so there's a moderately reasonable
attempt at, at the full name.
So this around 800 current era.
And he wrote one book in about 1825, On
The Calculation with Hindu Numerals.
That was a book on arithmetic using Hindu
numerals .
And then a few years later, he wrote this
book and in the title of that book,
you'll see that phrase al-jabr, and
that's where we get the word algebra
from, because this was the world's first
recognizable algebra book, and that was
the focus of the book.
And that phrase in there, at the end of
it, really means restoration and
confrontation.
Those terms that we saw a moment ago in
connection with Diophantus.
The way of solving an equation move
things from one side to the other and
remove equal terms from both sides.
if you want to translate the whole thing
and again I've got this translation from
one of the leading scholars of the
period.
The Abridged Book on Calculation by
Restoration and Confrontation would be a
modern scholarly translation.
it's usually however, known among
scholars as just the abridged book on
algebra, because nowadays we would just
refer to restoration and confrontation as
just as the key methods for solving
equations, so it's algebra.
And the question that people like me get
asked when we teach students that are not
necessarily enamored buy mathematics, is
not at Stanford, but I mean if you go
elsewhere, then they'll say, what's this
useful for?
Is this really any use?
Well, let's go back to the source.
al-Khwarizmi's book is essentially a
modern algebra book.
You know, the lang, the language has
changed and we've got better examples,
and these days we have full color
illustrations and all that kind of thing.
But if you go back there you've really
got the beginnings of the modern algebra
book.
and al-Khwarizmi answers the question.
Here's what he says, what is easiest and
most useful in arthritic?
This is what the book is about, such as
men constantly requiring cases of
inheritance, legacies, partition,
lawsuits, and trade, and in all their
dealings with one another, or where the
measuring of lands, the digging of
canals, geometric computations and other
objects of various sorts and kinds of
concern .
It doesn't get more fundamental than
that, this is basic commerce.
This is how people trade and live and
enter legal dealings and deal with their
finances.
So algebra was introduced for very very
practical reasons.
One thing that is characteristic of
almost all the writings of what's known
as Arabic mathematics, meaning the
writings that were preserved in the
Arabic writing.
and that, you know, all sorts of people
were involved.
there were Persians, there were people
whose natural language was Arabic there
were Jews, there were Christians floating
around, there were people floating around
in the Middle East all over the place,
and in Spain, doing work.
And But it was the, the language in which
just, just as we talk about Greek
mathematics, much of which is done by
Egyptians, but it Greek was the language
it was echoed in, it was this phrase
Arabic mathematics which really means it
was recorded and stored in the Arabic
language.
okay, but its, it gets extremely useful.
I'm very particular, certainly the
interest, I love the Greek's interest.
Was very much one of a sort of leisurely
pursuit, an intellectual pursuit.
The Greeks, as famously known, thought of
mathematics, particularly geometry, as
an, as a, as a, as a pursuit of the mind,
something for the leisured classes to do,
something to think about to, to, to
improve your mind.
go to the Muslim world in the 8th or 9th
century, it was driven primarily through
very practical reasons.
They were engineers, they were traders.
And so [COUGH], this was designed to be
an, to improve the way of doing business.
[COUGH] there's an image from a I, I
forget the date on that one but it's an
image that managed to get all over the
date from one version of that book but if
you look at the contents of the of the
book and this is not meant to be a
translation from there this is just a
summary from the contents of the book.
This is it, basically in that book he
takes linear quadratic equations.
And actually at the end of last week we
had, I had a discussion with a couple of
people as to why there was this huge
focus on quadratics?
And you know, and the answer is if you're
a practical person, you can do an awful
lot in the world with linear equations.
Sometimes things change at different
rates and linear doesn't work.
The next best thing is quadratic, and
within, within a certain range of
tolerance, that's as far as you need to
go.
You know, even an exponential curve looks
quadratic over a small interval, so it's
just a reasonably good approximation.
Look through physics books [COUGH].
Physics books, classical physics books,
are full of linear and quadratic
equations.
Well, it's just because that was already
difficult enough and good enough for
doing an awful lot of things.
You know, and as physics developed,
people would realize that there were o-,
there were higher order terms that you
needed to take into account, but of a
reasonable areas of, of, of accuracy that
will do.
Same with computer graphics, right?
You, you can, you can draw almost with a
computer graphics package that will draw
straight lines and quadratics.
You just put them together in a suitable
way.
So these, you can, you can do piece wise,
linear and piece wise quadratic curves,
and get all kinds of nice shapes.
[COUGH] Okay so this was really
developing machinery that was really
useful.
you might ask yourself, why regard these
as different?
Because we don't today, we just talk
about quadratics, which is ax squared
plus bx plus c equals 0, and that's a
quadratic.
Well, the reason was they didn't have
negative numbers in their calculations.
So they had to take account of whether
the a's and the b's, these were all
positive, so you had to put them on
different sides in the first place.
In fact, their conception of negative
numbers was really unusual.
the confronta-, those words restoration
and confrontation, confrontation is
really sort of easy.
You've got equal things on both sides
that confront each other.
Well, if they confront each other, you
can remove them.
Restoration means, you restore the value,
instead of dealing with a negative term,
so they, they wouldn't have something
like 10 minus X.
What they would say is you've got a 10
and it's, it loses weight.
It goes on a diet and it loses x pounds,
xo you've got a slimmed down 10, but it's
still positive.
You know, you gotta you take something
then you work with it you get a number,
you do something and at the end you
restore it's value.
Which we would say is adding expect able
size, but that's not how they thought
about it they, they, they didn't have
subtraction and they didn't have
negatives, so they just thought of
diminished quantities that were still 10
minus x was still a 10.
It was a 10 that has lost weight, you're
reason with that then you restore to the
end.
It's hard to get into that mindset now
because we know there's other way of
thinking about it.
But that was, that was how we, if you
want to understand the writing, you have
to understand that they didn't have
subtraction.
You couldn't subtract from both sides,
you can diminish something.
And was where the word restoration came
from, you restored the value of the
thing.
[MUSIC]
.