Okay[COUGH].
Here's a very famous, a historically
famous problem, from al-Khwarizmi's
Algebra.
This is how it was written.
Doesn't look like algebra today but it's
all language, all words.
Let me give you, well actually, let me
read it out.
Because this was a, a, a modern
translation, a fairly literal
translation, from al-Khwarizmi's book.
If some one say, you divide 10 into two
parts, multiply the 1 by itself; it will
be equal to the other taken 81 times.
Computation; You say, 10 less thing
that's going to be a 10 but it is less
something.
It's a diminish 10, multiplied by itself
is a 100 plus a square less 20 things.
So the less doesn't mean you're
subtracting, it means it's reduced
somehow and this is equal to 81 things.
Separate the 20 things from a hundred and
square and a square and add them to 81.
It will then be a 100 plus a square,
which is equal to a 101 roots.
Halve the roots; the moiety and we'll
come back to that in a minute, is 50 and
a half.
Multiply this by itself, it is 2550 and a
quarter.
Subtract from this 100 the remainder is
2450 and a quarter.
Extract the root from this, it is 49 and
a half.
Subtract this from the moiety of the
roots, which is 50 and a half.
There remains 1, and this is one of the
two parts.
most of us would find that quite
challenging to to understand let me take
you out of your misery[LAUGH] they were
solving this.
You've got a 10 slimmed down by an amount
x, you're squaring it and you get 81.
That's the solution to that.
And actually if you follow that through
that's just the, the sort of like the way
we might solve the equation.
I'm not going to go through the details,
but it's sort of like the way you, you
sort of follow that through and
understand that what you would do.
bearing in mind that they didn't have
negatives, but they could move things
from one side to the other.
I'm going to move on,[LAUGH] I, you, it
was really just, the, the, I, I didn't
want you to spend a lot of time, just to
show you that the way it was laid out
much simpler, we would think, to just
solve that equation because we reduced
algebra to very much just symbolic
manipulation.
Well the point about solving that
quadratic is you can do it without
switching your brain on.
Once you know the method, you can just
grind the handle.
It's very much algorithmic.
Okay so that was al-Khwarizmi.
I will mention that al-Khwarizmi, because
he was describing procedures for doing
arithmetic, especially in his first book.
Well actually both books.
Gave birth to the modern word algorithm.
So the word algorithm for computation
procedure is derived from al-Khwarizmi' .
So he, he left the word with 2 words
algorithm and algebra.
Pretty, pretty significant.
Okay, so that how al-Khwarizmi, and
there's another nice picture for one of
the books.
Then the next major figure almost
immediately afterwards was Abu Kamil a
guy who wrote a, many books at least 10
of which we know.
did a whole bunch of things really
dramatic individual, remarkable
individual.
he actually used that equation to solve,
to calculate the side of a regular
pentagon.
some very remarkable piece of work.um,
and the guy was so sort of amazing and
obsessive one might say that in one case
he looked at many, what is known as
indeterminate problems, problems where
there's not a unique solution but there
are many solutions, and in one case he
actually went through and found 2,005, 7,
676 solutions.
Hand calculation of all those many
solutions.
well you think, there were fewer
distractions then, right?
>> Yes.
>> So, it was even so that's, that's pretty
remarkable.
the next major figure, and there were,
there were a lot of people involved.
This was a huge en, en, enterprise going
on, I'm just mentioning some of the more
famous people.
And then we've got al-Karaji recognized
that the sequence.
Well that first remark is really a modern
interpretation of what he did.
You have to sort of read it with modern
eyes, but essentially he realized that
you can keep running up the exponents
indefinitely.
likewise from a modern perspective, he
discovered proof by induction.
The method of proof by induction where
you prove the first case and then you're
sure that if it's true for n it's true
for n plus 1, for those of you who've
been through that kind of an education.
it's not explicit in his work but it's
certainly implicit and some of the
historians I talked to said that yeah
it's a little bit of a stretch to call it
induction.
but from my perspective as a
mathematician it was induction.
it depends how you define it.
I could certainly look at it and see
induction.
and he verified this which is typically
done today by induction, that the sum of
the first n cubed is that formula.
I think I should add some, I think that
problem is on the test, the problem sheet
that I'm handing out to my student in my
online class today.
If it's not today, it's on Wednesday, so,
don't tell them.
[LAUGH] Right?
I think, I think I'm asking them to prove
this one as an example of induction
proofs.
he wrote at least three books.
then there's the famous Omar Khayyam no
more in the west as a poet I never
thought his poetry was that good but his
mathematics was brilliant and I think the
fact he's known as a poet reflects more
on our values in society where we value
poetry over mathematics.
I, I wouldn't change the balance the
other way I'd say.
I wouldn't want to put them on a battle,
because they're both important things.
okay yeah but he certainly did some
spectacular mathematics, worked on
astronomy, calendar reform, a very
significant figure very, very detailed
cataloguing of things.
All the possible kinds of equations,
relating them to geometric constructions.
His, his book is, is easily available in
at least three translations, including
one as recent as last year.
so if cubic's using very intricate
instructions involving conic sections
methods that are sometimes taught today
in, in, in classes of fork or some kind
of thing.
and actually looked at the issue of
things that could, could, couldn't be
solved by ruler and compass methods.
So was very much into the kind of things
that are still.
At least in high school geometry courses,
still very much a focus.
I know, a rather nice picture from this
manuscript of the cubic equation in this
section of conic section.
Okay, and then this amazing person, did a
whole bunch of things.
certainly a child prodigy, he wrote over
80 books and articles got involved in all
sorts of other enterprises.
al-Samaw'al.
And this is really a sort of a quotation
from, I mean, this is a quotation from
one of his writings.
He said that algebra involves quote,
"Operating on unknowns using all the
arithmetical tools, in the same way as
the arithmetician operates on the known."
That nails that distinction between
algebra and, and arithmetic.
You're using arithmetical tools but,
you're doing it a different level of
abstraction.
You're doing it on the unknowns, which
means you're sort of doing logical
reasoning with them.
You're doing qualitative reasoning in an
arithmetic framework as opposed to
calculating with the numbers.
And he, among the things he did was true
of this result for the sums of the
squared.
Again, that's expressing it in modern
notation.
So absent and notation you've got an
awful lot of modern algebra been on this
period.
but the story then picks up by Leonardo
and then if we're satisfied with Leonardo
we can pick up essentially the same story
in terms of spreading the word with Steve
Jobs, so that was a quick tour through
algebra, the history of algebra up to,
essentially to modern times.
>> [MUSIC]
Stanford University.