[BLANK_AUDIO].
[MUSIC].
Most of us encounter probabilities in
games of chance.
If a die is rolled a great many times,
then on average the one will come up one
sixth of the time.
Its probability is one sixth.
The basic mathematics of calculating
probabilities was worked out by the
French mathematicians Fermat and Pascal
in the seventeenth century.
Bayes added an intriguing new twist to
that theory.
He showed how what you already know can
change the odds.
[MUSIC].
>> These people, dressed as they are,
come from all over the United States to
make deals here in the marketplace of
America, Let's Make A Deal.
And now here's America's top trader, TV's
big dealer, Monte Hall.
[NOISE].
>> One way to understand Bayes' idea is
by considering the probability puzzle
first by the contestants in the popular
1950s TV game show, Let's Make a Deal.
>> [INAUDIBLE] it's time for the big
deal.And the big deal tonight
is[CROSSTALK].
>> Each week, at a particular moment in
the show, the host, Monty Hall, asked the
contestant to guess which of the three
doors concealed a prize[CROSSTALK].
>> Door Number 2, Door Number 3, which
one would you like?
>> Let's say you choose Door 1.
You have a one third probability of
winning.
And that's exactly the same for the other
two doors.
Here's where it gets interesting.
Monty Hall doesn't let you open your
door.
Instead, he opens of the other two doors.
Say, Door 3, revealing an empty space.
Now, he asks you if you want to change
your choice, from Door 1 to Door 2.
So, what do you do?
Do you stick with your original choice or
do you switch?
If you think it makes no difference, then
you're wrong.
If you switch, it actually doubles your
chance of being right.
Here's why.
When you choose Door 1, the probability
the prize is behind it, is one third.
That means the chance that the prize is
behind one of the other two doors is one
third plus one third or two thirds.
When Monte Hall eliminates Door 3, those
odds pass to Door 2 alone.
Thus, switching from Door 1 to Door 2
doubles your chances of winning.
[MUSIC].
>> Yes, that represents a $50 gift
certificate from Big Boy Family
Restaurants.
Famous for their original[CROSSTALK].
>> Bayes would have had no problem
explaining what's happened.
It's all to do with prior information.
Because the host knows which door has the
prize behind it, and opens one that
doesn't, this knowledge changes the odds.
[SOUND].
Not convinced?
[MUSIC].
Well try the puzzle again with a 100
doors.
Let's say you choose door 33.
Now, the host opens all the remaining
doors except one.
Would you still stick or would you
switch?
The chance of your guess being right is
only 1 in a 100.
But as Bayes would tell you, the host's
knowledge has changed the odds for the
remaining door to 99 hundreths.
It's tricky, isn't it?
What this shows is that it can be hard
figuring the odds when someone has prior
knowledge.