[MUSIC].
I live and breath mathematics.
I'm aware of the fact that mathematics is
been invented all the time.
And yet, I meet people regularly at
parties and elsewhere who say, well, you
know, what's the interest in mathematics?
Didn't the Greeks sort of finish that
2,000 years ago?
And you know, I think, oh my goodness,
no.
>> Stanford University Mathematician
Keith Devlin knows that there are many
reasons to be excited about math, and the
new ways math is being used today,
something called knot theory for example.
>> Knot theory actually begins in the
middle of the nineteenth century and it's
what the name suggests.
It's the mathematical study of knots.
The kind of knots you tie in a piece of
string.
And what distinguishes one knot from
another knot is the pattern whereby you
wrap the string around itself.
But then, in the 1980s, biologists
started to team up with mathematicians,
not to think about the kind of knots that
tie them that we can tie in pieces of
string.
But to look at the knots in which our own
DNA wraps itself, when it gets inside the
cell, when it, when it lives inside the
cell, and what a virus does to, to, to
sort of manipulate that knot pattern.
And so, it, it's, it's close to the stage
now where peoples' lives will be saved
because mathematicians who know about
knot theory have teamed up with
biologists to look at the fundamental.
Maybe, maybe some of the most fundamental
knots that there are, the knots that are
right down inside our own cells.
>> Devlin spreads the word while
wearing many hats.
Math professor, radio personality,
television content adviser, author, and
lecturer.
>> I've already mentioned the iPod
designed just down the road here in sunny
Cupertino.
well, those guys are geeks, down the
road.
They are the kind of geeks that
understand this kind of stuff.
So the Fourier's theory that's part of
the mathematics, behind what's going on
in the you know, and you know, and these
guys now, you, you've got 60 gigabyte
memories in some of these things.
That's enormous amount of storage.
You can store movies in some, not this
one, but a bigger one, you can store
movies in some of these.
That's because of very, very effective
compression techniques.
What these things store isn't music or
videos, it's numbers, billions and
billions of numbers.
>> When you're listening to your
favorite song, it's easy to forget that
math is behind what makes digital music
devices and similar technology work.
But just what specific mathematical
innovation makes this great escape
possible?
An important one is wavelet theory,
another form of new math.
>> A wavelet is a very, very simple
short little wave that will consist of
maybe one little blip or just a couple of
blips that can be described by a simple
mathematical formula.
>> If this doesn't look simple, it's
because simplicity is relative.
Equations for curves can be much more
complex.
>> Wavelets were first discovered, or
invented if you like, early in the
twentieth century.
But it was only in the 1980s or 90s that
mathematicians began to develop methods
for dealing with wavelets that allows us
to take these days, a sound wave, it
could be a rock group or a two hundred
piece orchestra.
And reduce them to a mathematical
combination of these little individual
wavelets as they're called, which are
little pieces of waves that don't keep
going on forever.
Actually, what's happening is you're
hearing music that's been created right
there, especially for you.
Because what's stored inside the device
Is instructions, it's an instruction set
to recreate that music.
That instruction set is written in the
language of mathematics, because the
information that's stored in order to
recreate the music is actually hundreds,
thousands, maybe millions and billions of
numbers.
One way to think about wavelets and how
they're used is to think in terms of
building a house.
If I were to give you, say five or six
different kinds of bricks, then you know
and I know that you could go and find an
architect who could use those [UNKNOWN]
different types of bricks to build houses
of all sizes and all shapes, because it's
all a matter of how you put those bricks
together.
Wavelet theory is essentially the same.
It shows you how you can take any sound
wave or any video signal, any, any image,
and how you can build it up from
individual little building blocks.
In this case, the building blocks are
little graphical waves.
>> [MUSIC] And although, wavelet theory
was developed only decades ago, a short
time in the history of mathematics ideas,
it was French mathematician Joseph
Fourier who paved the way in the early
1800s.
>> He showed that if you take any sound
wave, actually any kind of wave
whatsoever, you can split it up into
component sine waves.
A sine wave is the simple up down wave
that you get when you hit a tuning fork.
You can take any sound wave and split
that up into individual components.
You need a lot of them, hundreds or
thousands of them.
Actually, the mathematics says you need
infinitely many of them.
What Fourier assured, was that if you
take a sound wave, a complicated wave
like this one right on the top here, you
can actually make that by taking very,
very many sound waves.
Like the one at the bottom of different
amplitudes and frequencies, add them all
together, and get the complicated sound
wave that we see here.
So, this complicated sound wave at the
top can actually be built out of
components, all of which looks like this
one on the bottom.
>> It's like the sound of a choir.
When you listen to many people singing
together, you hear a group of voices in
unison.
In effect, a single sound.
Of course, what you're listening to is
not just a single sound, it's made up of
dozens of voices.
If you are able to hear each of these
singers separately, you could pick out
one person's voice.
The unified sound illustrates the basis
of Fourier's theory.
>> [MUSIC] Another way to get a handle
on Fourier's theory is to use the tuning
fork.
We'll hit the tuning fork, and if you
look on the oscilloscope screen, what
you're getting is an image, a visual
image of the sound.
And because it's a turning fork making a
pure sound, a pure note, what we're
seeing is a sine curve.
If we were to take a whole bunch of
tuning forks and put them together, then
we would be able to create any sound we
wanted to if we did it the right way.
For example, if I take another tuning
fork and I hit the tuning fork, it's a
different size tuning fork, I'm getting a
different sound.
>> If you look at the oscilloscope
tracings from both turning forks
together, you can see how the second wave
looks like it's moving faster to the
left.
[MUSIC] This is due to its slightly
greater frequency, but it's still a sine
curve.
>> It's because the wave changes in its
dimensions that when you put them
together, when you put lots of them
together, what results is not just one
big sine curve.
But actually, one very complicated curve
with all sorts of different wiggles in
it, that when you play it back could be
indeed Beethoven's ninth symphony.
>> That's part of the basis for today's
digital music players.
But Fourier's discovery of how sine waves
can be combined to make more complex
waves has now been advanced into uses of
the simpler little pieces of waves or
wavelengths.
Rather than going on and on endlessly, as
a sign wave does, wavelets, or wave
particles start and stop.
Why is that important?
Because the mathematical description of a
sound wave in terms of sine waves is very
cumbersome.
Where as the description in terms of
wavelets is much simpler and new
applications for wavelets are always
being developed.
The FBI uses wavelets to help encode
their fingerprint database.
Wavelets are beginning to help with
weather forecasting.
Keith Devlin, like so many other
mathematicians, is excited to know that
new mathematics, like recently developed
wavelet theory, are still being invented
as our new connections between different
types of math, and of course, the new
high tech developments born out of all
this.
>> mathematics is invented all the
time.
Most of the mathematical knowledge we
have, over half the mathematical
knowledge we have, was invented by
mathematicians who were living today.
Mathematics is an incredibly vibrant
subject.
I like it, I'm excited by it, and I want
to, there's a natural human instinct to
want to share your excitement with
others.
So when I, when I wrote my book on New
Mathematics, it was an attempt to convey
to others.
First of all, that New Mathematics is
happening all the time.
And secondly, that it's exciting, cool
stuff.
And thirdly, and deliberately thirdly,
it's important stuff that will in fact
effect everyone's lives 20 or 30 years
from now.