[MUSIC].
This is the story of how a group of
gamblers fleeced the casinos for
millions.
[NOISE]
>> The buzz for me was the potential.
It was unlimited.
And I could make money without punching a
clock.
I could have a ton of fun.
Certainly women were going to love me.
It was great.
>> I was excited about the idea of
goading death with [UNKNOWN].
David and Goliath kind of situation.
>> And beating them.
And them not even realizing we're beating
them.
>> But these were no ordinary gamblers.
They were brilliant students with an
extraordinary secret, that meant they
simply couldn't lose.
But Thorp thought he could do better,
because he'd realized there was something
special about Blackjack.
The odds of winning worked in a different
way to almost every other gambling game.
[MUSIC] In terms of mathematical
probability, gambling games work in one
of two ways.
In Russian roulette, a bullet is loaded
into a barrel of six chambers.
[MUSIC] [SOUND] Every time the barrel is
spun, there's a one in six chance of
firing the bullet.
[MUSIC]
>> When you're playing Russian
roulette, if you spin the chamber before
you pull the trigger every time.
[MUSIC] Then each pull of the trigger is
an independent event.
The gun has no memory.
Spinning the chamber destroys all memory
of what's happened before.
>> [MUSIC] In other words, spin the
barrel every time and the probability of
firing the bullet never changes.
It's always one in six.
[SOUND] But there's another way of
playing Russian roulette, where you don't
spin the barrel between shots but just
keep on pulling the trigger.
>> If it doesn't go off, and you pull
the trigger again, the second pull of the
trigger is not an independent event,
because the odds have changed of you
getting an explosion.
>> Each time the trigger is pulled, the
probability of firing the bullet falls.
Initially, from one in six, right down to
a dead certainty.
The odds change because they are
dependent on what has happened on the
previous pull of the trigger.
What Ed Thorp realized, was this
dependence is exactly what happens in a
game of Blackjack.
And it's because of how the cards must be
dealt.
Critically in most casino games after
each round the cards are always returned
to the deck so they can be played in the
next hand.
But in Blackjack, used cards are not
returned, but set aside.
This means the odds of getting winning
cards change as the game progresses,
because the deck is made up of fewer and
fewer cards for every hand.
>> The thing that makes Blackjack
different is each hand is not an
independent event, the cards actually do
have a memory of the previous hands and a
good player can also have a memory of
those previous hands.
[BLANK_AUDIO]