Hello, I'm Keith Devlin.
Welcome to this online course on
Mathematical Thinking.
The goal of the course is to help you
develop a valuable mental ability.
A powerful way of thinking that people
have developed to over 3000 years.
What I want to do today, is get you ready
for the course,
and tell you a little bit about the way
the course will work.
I'm doing this because for most of you,
this will be a very
different perspective, on what mathematics
is.
Apart from the final two lectures, there's
very little mathematical content in the
course.
And you won't learn any new mathematical
procedures.
But mathematical thinking is essential if
you want to make
the transition from high school math to
university level mathematics.
The quickest way to learn what
mathematical thinking
is, is to take a course like this.
So, by the time we're finished, you should
know what it is.
But for now, let me give you an analogy.
If we compare mathematics with the
automotive
world, school math corresponds to learning
to drive.
In the automotive equivalent to college
mathematics, in
contrast, you will learn how a car works,
how to maintain and repair it.
And, if you pursue the subject far enough,
how to design and build your own car.
The only prerequisite for the course is
completion or pending completion of high
school mathematics.
That means many people could take the
course and find it valuable.
In particular, a key feature of
mathematical thinking is thinking outside
the box.
In contrast, they key to success in high
school
math was to learn to think inside the box.
It's because
thinking outside the box is such a
valuable ability in
today's world, that this course could be
valuable to many people.
But my primary students is someone in
their
final year of high school, or their first
year at college or university, who's
thinking of
majoring in mathematics or a math
dependent subject.
If that's you, than you'll probably find
that transition
from high school mathematics to college
level pure abstract
mathematics difficult.
I certainly did, and so did most
mathematicians I know.
Not because that mathematics gets harder.
Once you successfully made the transition,
I think you'll
agree that college math is in many ways
easier.
What causes the problem is the change in
emphasis.
At high school, the focus is primarily
on mastering procedures, to solve various
kinds
of problems.
That gives a subject very much the
flavor of a cookbook full of mathematical
recipes.
Thinking inside boxes.
At University, the focus is on learning to
think a different way.
To think like a mathematician.
Thinking out side the box.
Well that's not true of all college math
courses.
Those designed for science and engineering
students
are often very much in the same vein
as the courses you had in high school.
It's the courses that form the bulk of the
mathematics major that are different.
But some of those courses are usually
required
for more advanced work in science and
engineering.
So if you're a student in those
disciplines you may
also find yourself faced with this
different kind of mathematics.
If you did well at math in school,
you probably got good at recognizing
different kinds
of problems.
So you could apply different techniques
you learned.
At university, you have to learn how to
approach a new problem.
One that doesn't quite fit any template
you're familiar with.
It comes down to leaning how to think
about a problem in a certain way.
The first key step, is learn to stop
looking
for a formula to apply, or a procedure to
follow.
Approaching a new problem by looking for a
template, or worked example in a
textbook or present it on YouTube and
then just changing the numbers often won't
worked.
Eh, sometimes it will.
So all that work you did at high school
won't go to waste.
But it isn't enough for many of your
college math courses.
If you can't solve the problem by looking
for a template to follow,
or a formula to plug some numbers into, or
a procedure to apply.
What do you do?
The answer is you think about the problem
a certain way.
Not the form of the problem.
That's probably what you were taught to do
at school, and it served you well there.
Rather, you have to look at what the
problem actually says.
Sounds as though
it ought to be easy, but most of
us initially find it extremely hard and
very frustrating.
It doesn't come quickly or easily.
You have to work at it.
You're going to have to accept going a lot
slower than you're used to.
Most of the time, you won't feel as though
you're making any progress.
Your goal has to be understanding, not
doing.
You should definitely try all the
exercises.
They're there to aid your understanding.
You should also work with others.
Few of us can master this crucial shift in
thinking on our own.
That part's crucial.
A lot of what we'll be doing is not so
much focused
on right and wrong, but on learning how to
think about a problem.
Yeah, sure, at the end of the day,
solutions are right and wrong.
But usually, there are many
different right answers, or different ways
to the right answer, and many wrong ones.
When you're learning how to think
mathematically, it's how
and why you got something right or wrong
that's important.
The only way to find that out, to find out
how well you're
doing is for somebody else to look at your
attempt and critique your work.
It's not possible to automate the grading
process.
Maybe one day artificial intelligence will
have advanced far enough for
a course like this to be automated, though
frankly, I doubt it.
But right now, you need feedback from
other people.
For a regular class here at Stanford, the
professor an
the graduate student TA's, grade students
work, an provide feedback.
With an open online
course like this, where there are
many thousands of students, that's not
possible.
So we have to go about things a different
way.
I've designed the course so that the
benefit comes primarily
from doing the work and discussing it with
other students.
Getting it right is important in
mathematics, but in a Massively Open
Online Course, a MOOC, like this, there's
no way to guarantee that.
Incidentally, not being sure if we are
right until others
have seen our work, is very familiar, to
we mathematicians.
Even very famous mathematicians, have had
the experience, of
thinking they've solved a problem, and
writing it, writing it
up, writing out their solution and sending
it off for
publication, only for an anonymous referee
to find an error.
In mathematics, there is such a thing as
right
and wrong, but deciding between them can
be very difficult.
So even the professionals have to live
with
never being sure whether they're right or
not.
Part of this introductory session is a
reading assignment.
It gives you a bit of a history that
should
explain why today's mathematics students
need a course such as this.
In lecture one, there'll be a short quiz
on the reading.
Let me say a few words about the quizzes.
If you were in one of my regular physical
classes, I'd talk with
you to find out if you had understood the
materials sufficiently to progress.
But with a Massively Open Online Course, a
MOOC, that's not possible.
You have to monitor yourself.
The quizzes are one way to help you do
that.
I'll say a little bit more about the
quizzes later.
But before you start lecture one, please
read a file called Background Reading.
It's just over six pages long.
It's a PDF file, so you can download it
and read it offline.
Well, now you know what an intellectual
quiz looks like.
The next thing I suggest you do is view
the video, finding your way around the
course website.
It will point you to some particularly
important
things to check out before you start the
course.