Before you start the course proper,
you should spend some time
finding out where on the website.
There's a lot of information there,
but it does take some getting used to,
particularly if this is your
first course over Mooc.
Let me start with the homepage,
that's the page behind me.
This is the one you saw when you first
logged onto the actual course site.
The homepage is where you should look
first every time you logon to the site,
because that's where I post reminders,
updates and other important information.
Now, let's look at the main navigation
bar on the left hand side of the screen.
As you'll see,
it's divided into four sections.
The first section has just two links, both
to important course information pages.
At the top, there's a link
to the daily bulletin board.
The main content of the site's homepage,
you can see behind me.
Below that is the cost time table.
A PDF file, I recommend you print off and
keep with you.
It lists all the key deadlines,
so you can plan ahead.
If I have to change
anything in the schedule,
I'll post a bulletin board
message on the site's homepage.
By the way, don't try to print off
PDF files from your web browser.
Browsers don't always
display PDF files well.
In particular,
they can miss mathematical symbols.
Always download the file and
print it off using Adobe Reader.
Below those two links
is the second section,
which lists the parts of the website
where you actually do things.
Discussion forums, videos,
problem sets,
in lecture quiz duplicates, and
finally the test flight process,
which we can largely ignore for now.
The video section is where,
in addition to the videos themselves,
you'll find links to the assignment
sheets that accompany each lecture and
to PDF versions of the problem sets.
I'll say a little bit about what
those terms, problem set and
assignment mean in a minute.
Below the course activities,
is a section called Course Information.
Before you start work on the course,
you should look through the first
four items in this section, as well as
the last one on the grading policy.
The first two describe the nature of
the course and how it's structured.
The first few times I gave this course,
some students felt bewildered by
the way the course progressed.
Mostly, they ran into difficulties because
they haven't paid attention to those two
course information sections.
Though I have since reworded them to
try and make things a bit clearer.
The course goals page is fairly long, but
provides some fairly important
background information about the course.
In particular,
it tells you what to expect and why.
If you're taking the course for
a certificate, you have two options,
the basic course and the extended course.
If you complete the basic course,
which lasts eight weeks, you'll
receive statement of accomplishment.
If you continue for two further weeks and
complete all parts of the test flight
process, you'll receive a statement
of accomplishment with distinction.
You don't have to make
an official selection.
Simply decide at the end of eight
weeks whether you want to stop and
a collect statements of accomplishments or
continue for
the final two weeks to get
a distinction certificates.
Notice that the certificates
are awarded for
completion of the appropriate course,
not the grade you get.
You will receive your aggregate score,
but it will be
in the cover letter to your certificate,
not on the certificate itself.
This is because the points awarded have
little significance outside the course.
Their relevance is within the course.
The course treats points like the points
that are awarded in a video game.
They have significance inside the game,
but no value outside.
You should use them as a guide
to measure your progress.
If you're new to the topics
covered in this course,
a grade of 35% on a problem
set can be a good result.
Just as happens in many video games,
to get high scores, you have to
keep coming back and trying again.
A bit lower down the page, there's also
section on the underlying cause pedagogy.
Chances are, unless you've been
a student at a good college or
university, you may never have experienced
a course with a structure as this one.
You should definitely read
this section carefully.
Also, watch the 20 minute
video linked to it.
The pedagogy paragraph and that video
explain why you don't see my tutorial
explanations of assigned work until
after you've attempted to complete it.
The course isn't about whether you
can solve the assigned problems.
It's about attempting them.
To put it bluntly, if you can do
most of the assigned problems,
you really don't need this course.
The next section, course structure,
describes how the course is
constructed to embody those
underlying pedagogic principles.
Like the previous page, it's long and
packed with valuable information.
The one point I want to emphasize,
is the statement that the assignments and
problem sets are the heart of the course.
It's when you're struggling with those
problems that the actual learning will
take place and you will struggle.
Perhaps not in the first couple of weeks,
but for sure, before the course is done.
Though the lecture and tutorial videos are
the visible part of a Mooc, in my course,
their purpose is mostly to give you
a bit of background information and
provide examples of mathematical thinking.
They're not instructional, and
they won't show you how to do
any of the assignment problems.
Now it may not be what you're used to,
but it is how mathematics
is learned at university.
It has to be done that way.
Since the goal is to acquire
the ability to solve a novel problem,
it doesn't help you, for me to show
you how to solve specific examples.
The only way to acquire that ability,
is to keep trying and
failing, until you get it.
That's why this course rewards time
spent and effort, not performance.
The only attempts you make that
are graded at all are the problem sets,
in both versions of the course.
The problem sets consist of typical
assignment problems, for which you
enter an answer on the course website and
receive a machine-assigned grade.
The primary purpose of those grades is to
give you some feedback on your progress.
This is particularly helpful for
students taking this course a second,
or even a third time.
The only other relevance
of the machine grids,
is to determine what constitute
completion of the course.
Check out the last page in the course
information section, grading and
statements of accomplishment, to see
how the final grades are computed, and
certificates awarded.
I'll leave you to check out
the remaining parts of the website,
once the course is under way.
For now, just concentrate on
the pages I just discussed.
Finally, if you want to know more
about the design of this course and
pedagogy behind it,
check out my blog, mooctalk.org.
I've been blogging about this course since
I started work on the first version,
back in spring 2012.
On the course readings page,
I provide links to some particular posts
I think you definitely should read.
I know from experience that many students
need to know why things are set up
a certain way.
Many of those blog posts were written in
response to student comments from previous
sessions of this course.
So chances are, by now,
any question you have will already
have been addressed on that blog.
Okay.
I suggest you now spend some time becoming
very familiar with the site structure and
the parts I've drawn your attention to.
You can look into
the evaluation rubric and
check out test flight once
the course is underway.
They're not relevant in
the first couple of weeks.
And the ride is about to begin.