.
>> So Paul and Keith and I are together to
discuss the reincarnation of the
mathematical course that's been online.
It's, it's, it's not a 1.2.
It's actually the introduction of
mathematical thinking, new and improved.
>> I would call it version 0.2.
>> Okay [laugh].
>> 0.1 was last September.
This is 0.2.
And we might meet, we might, we might
reach a better release version[LAUGH] in a
couple of years time.
Of course we're releasing it.
>> So is this a matter of your deciding to
change content, or is this, the changes
are more a response to learning about
MOOCs as you go along?
>> Partly, we're learning about, its the
same content in, in some sense.
It's partly learning about MOOCs, and it's
partly the feedback we got from the
students the first time around.
The, the, we got a lot of ideas for what
we thought, what we think might be
improvements.
We won't really know whether they're
improvements until we run them out and
test them.
>> Paul, what do you see as the big
difference here between teaching this same
content to a flesh and blood classroom
[LAUGH]with students in front of you?
>> There's a lot of differences.
I think one of the biggest differences in
a MOOC is, is the, the need to plan ahead.
That in a normal classroom, you have a lot
of opportunity to kind of change what
you're doing dynamically in the moment.
Whereas, in a MOOC, you kind of have to
have everything set and ready to go before
the course even begins.
And that's where the second version, we
can make all these changes that we've, you
know, kind of thought up as we were going
the first time.
And it's like, oh, well, we can't put that
in right now[LAUGH] because the course is
already running.
But now we have a chance to put some of
those things in.
>> So, can you, can you give me an example
of one of the key changes you've made,
Keith?
>> One change, and this is the most
obvious one to the students, is last fall,
it was a seven week course.
This week, I've taken the same material
and spread it over ten weeks, because I
got a lot of feedback from students who
were clearly motivated, dedicated, were
doing fine, but they had lives to live.
They weren't full time students, and they
would say, look, but I got to week 5, and
I had to go on a business trip.
And there were two lectures in week 5.
If there had been one lecture in week 5, I
could have caught up at the end of the
week, but there were two lectures.
I had to drop out.
And so what I am doing is I am giving the
first two weeks over two lectures a week,
because it's very introductory.
From week three onwards, there's only one
lecture a week.
So someone who has to miss a couple of
days because they've got some commitments
will have time to catch up.
>> And that was born out by the, the some
of the survey data we collected.
The median age in the last course was in,
people in their mid 30s.
So it's not just, you know, high
schoolers, or early college students who
want to explore this area.
It's a, we have a lot of students who are,
you know, who are professionals who want
to come back and look at this kind of
stuff that maybe they, you know, had to
drop when they were in college or they
never got a chance to explore.
So, it's a very different kind of
population than traditional college.
>> It's almost counterintuitive that it
would take more weeks to do it, because
you figure, if it's an online course and
you have, you don't have to be there at 3
PM on Thursday, you have all day Thursday
to go check in there.
You would almost think it would go faster.
>>, The freedom in the scheduling.
>> Not with this kind of a course, because
the, and I kept telling my students this.
I kept putting it out on my blogs and so
forth.
That the bit that they see on the video,
that bit that's actually online, that just
sets the stage.
Because learning mathematics at this level
involves a lot of thinking on your own and
a lot of talking with other people and
struggling to master material.
So you could maybe watch a 30 minute video
that I give.
It may take you two or three hours of
intense thinking, off and on, to make
sense of that thing.
So if, I describe my role as really, the
conductor of an orchestra.
You know, I, I decide which tune they're
going to play, I raise the baton, and I
leave them to work and I go off and have a
cup of coffee somewhere.
>> [laugh].
>> And then I come back later and see how
they're doing and checking in because it's
really for them to learn.
I'm not really teaching.
I'm just setting the stage so they can
learn.
So there's a lot of time they need to make
sense of what I manage to get through in,
in 30 minutes on video.
>> And it gives a little bit more
flexibility having the course be over 10
weeks, even for people who could do it
faster.
They can still kind of, I mean, they can
still work fairly quickly in that 10
weeks.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And then, I mean, one of the things
Keith says throughout the videos is, you
have to do this slowly, you have to take
your time, you have to think about.
So even the people who are getting it, and
who are going quickly can still benefit
from having that extra time, I think.
>> So having had your, your base in
physical, you know, right there,
education, what's been your biggest shock?
What's been your biggest lesson?
>> Oh wow.
There were lots of little shocks, I think.
The thing that comes to mind is actually
not a shock, because I expected it was
going to happen, but I was sort of
surprised when it really did.
You know, I love teaching one on one with
a student.
I love teaching students in groups of
maybe five to ten.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Bring it up to 20, I've never, I always
try to cut my classes at 20 when I get
physical classes.
I've taught classes of 250 and 300.
That's the worst possible, because there's
no contact.
It's just an audience.
They're basically just wallpaper around
the room, and they're all on Facebook at
the same time anyway.
>> [laugh].
>> So there's no contact.
You would think 65,000 students, even
worse.
It's not 65,000 students.
It's 65,000 individual students.
Teaching on a MOOC is one on one.
You have a student sitting next to you.
But if someone watches my class, you
occasionally see my face, but that's just
to make human contact.
Most of what you see, is that hand and a
piece of paper.
The way we record them is an overhead
camera on my desk at home, piece of paper,
talking to a student, that in my mind is
sitting next to me, in conversational
terms going through some mathematics.
Now, the student can't answer back in real
time, which is a big problem.
>> Yes.
>> And we can and people like Paul are
going to try and help me to compensate for
that.
But it's basically sitting next to the
professor and talking to the professor and
trying to understand what's going on.
In other words, in a MOOC, you're teaching
1 student.
>> And well, well, Paul, when you talk
about the logistics of that, I mean, when
you have a teacher who's actually online,
on that time, changing things or just
putting it up, does, isn't there a natural
advantage for the student who's likewise
online at exactly the same time and
doesn't have that delayed reaction of 10
hours later coming on and, and seeing
basically a canned lesson instead of a
live lesson?
>> Yeah, that's, that's an interesting
question.
I mean, I think that there's from the
video perspective, since the videos are
all kind of prerecorded, I don't know if
there's too much of a difference.
Certainly it, within the forums, there are
times where, like, Keith or I will be
logged into the forums.
>> Right.
>> And if somebody posts a question right
then that one of us can address, there
could be some advantage there.
But actually, I think our experience was
in the first course we actually, I think,
intentionally try to stay out of the
forum, like, answering questions right
away, until there had been a fair amount
of discussion or if it felt like it had
gotten to a point that it was an
unproductive disagreement.
But there's actually so much value in, in
staying out of the way, and letting the
students discuss with each other in the
forums.
And our experience was, I mean you,
because people post in the forums and
there's going to be a response within ten
minutes, 15 minutes almost every time.
>> I'm expecting two kinds of people to
come.
I know there were a lot of people who took
the last course and had to bail.
And some who took the last course and
finished, but didn't do as well as they
thought, who have already emailed me and
said that they're definitely coming back
and they'd, they'd like to try it again.
So I'm expecting those to come back, and,
and they will see some changes.
There have been some changes.
They would be unwise to be seduced by the
fact that things looked remarkably the
same in the first couple of weeks, because
they do change as we move on.
There's a difference in emphasis in the
way some of the material's presented and
some of the things I'm asking them to do.
And they'll realize that as they go
through it.
And for people who are doing it the first
time, you've got the benefit of the fact
that we have now learned from our
mistakes.
Last time, it's going to be better than
last time.
Last time I went in to it thinking, if we
don't totally fail, crash and burn, it's a
success.
>> [laugh].
>> Yes.
>> So by that measure, it was a success.
We've set ourselves a standard now.
It was okay last time.
It was, it was actually one of the most
successful courses that Coursera would put
on at the time.
It was the second highest grossing in
terms of students that they've had.
>> Not bad.
>> So it was, it was doing pretty well.
That, may be the math guy thing that
helped there.
But it, but it did pretty well.
But that set us a bar, and we now
definitely, I mean, I will be disappointed
if we don't exceed that bar.
>> An individual can feel so involved and
so personally invested that they would
literally contact the instructor and say
I'm coming back.
>> Oh, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, no, they I mean, and, and in a
sense, we set them up for doing that.
Because one of the things I tried to
convey was getting a sense of me as a
person.
You know, I actually appear on camera.
And I didn't have to.
I could have done it like Khan Academy,
where you never see the person involved.
I want them to get a sense of me.
Because mathematics is dry, abstract,
decontextualized.
I think you need a person to make contact
of, you know.
I was their friendly grandfather, or the
uncle or whatever it was.
I thought that was really important.
>> Mm-hm.
>> But if you watch what I'm doing, I'm
actually not teaching.
I'm not telling them any material.
I'm talking about the course.
I'm trying to motivate them.
I'm the coach, if you like, saying you
know, you can do this.
Keep at it.
And it was making human contact.
You know, I've recorded it in the studio
into camera, eye contact.
But that was all about making contact with
a human being.
The moment we start talking about
mathematics, I drop out and it was just my
hand there.
So, it was all about making that human
contact.
So not surprisingly, they did feel and
responded.
They feel they knew me.
That was a trick.
It's like everybody knows the news reader
on their favorite TV channel.
>> Right.
>> It's a member of the family, because
they're in your living room every night at
6 o'clock.
That's powerful.
>> That's wonderful.
>> I wanted to use that.
>> Yeah, that's, that's actually a high,
high compliment.
>> And for, I mean, for all of the emails
that you got telling, telling you people
would come back.
The posts, we did a survey at the end of
the course last time and I would say there
must have been hundreds and hundreds of
people in the post survey when, in the
free response.
Instead of giving feedback on the course
they said, oh, I'm sorry I didn't finish.
I'll, [laugh], I'm going to do it better
next time.
Like, I mean,it was, it was amazing that,
I mean, so many people wanted, I think
they felt that personal connection in such
a way that they're like.
>> Yeah.
>> They didn't want to let us down by not
finishing the course.
>> Yeah, yeah,these, that's what
education's about.
>> [laugh].
>> The teacher, you know, teachers don't
really teach.
What they do is they inspire students to
learn.
>> Mm-hm.
>> I don't think we can, I don't think I
can teach anybody anything.
The best I can hope is to inspire them to
learn, because learning is the active
thing.
>> Right.
>> What teaching is, in some sense except
inspiration.
And so, my, I, I see my role as to inspire
them.
And, in a sense, it's an easy one, because
I love the subject.
And I like to inspire people.
You know, there's, there's, you have to
fake a lot in the medium.
>> Right.
>> But what you're not faking is your love
of the subject.
>> Yeah, or you wouldn't be there.
>> And that you're going to be there.
So I was very gratified that they
contacted me, because it meant that much
had worked.
You know, the one thing I couldn't do,
which I love doing with real students, is
when they come into your office, as they
do all the time, when you talk to them.
That's missing.
>> Yeah.
>> For, for those of us giving them,
there's a lot of, of interesting upsides.
The big downside is you never get to know
the students.
>> Mh-hm.
>> You know, we wouldn't be in the
business if we didn't like getting to know
students.
>> Absolutely.
>> Actually I've had some professors that
I'm a little bit suspicious about.
>> [laugh].
>> [laugh] But most of us love this thing.
>> There's one in every crowd.
[laugh] Well thanks guys.
>> Okay.
Thank you.
>> Abliged to.
.