In this video, I'll show you a little
about using the course evaluation rubric.
The most common use of an evaluation
rubric is to achieve uniformity in
grades when a team of experts is grading a
large collection of examinations.
The goal is to assign a reliable grade to
each candidate's work.
In particular, it's assumed that the
people doing the evaluation are
experienced graders.
In this course, we are using a rubric in a
very different way.
Not to help experts produce a reliable
grade of a piece of work.
But as a mechanism to help beginners learn
about proofs.
If you look at the rubric for the course,
you'll see
that it asks you to consider five
different features of proofs.
Logical correctness, clarity, opening,
stating the conclusion, and reasons.
I'll come to the sixth category later by
the way.
These are all important features of
proofs.
And for pedagogic reasons, are given equal
weight.
Here's why.
As
I state repeatedly throughout the course,
proofs do much
more than simply establish that some
statement is true.
Actually, in practice, they don't really
do that.
They simply provide evidence that
convinces
a reasonable person with sufficient
background knowledge.
But let's leave that issue for now.
If you look at the role played by proofs
in
mathematics, you discover that just as
important as logical correctness,
is the understandability of the proof by
an intended reader.
In fact, in practical terms,
understandablity's
[LAUGH] more important than logical
correctness.
There's probably no modern proof of more
than a few
pages that does not initially have a
logical flaw buried somewhere.
What makes proofs useful is as others can
not only detect errors.
But also have enough information to try to
correct them.
Proofs are as much about communication as
establishing truths.
Because we have to use simple examples to
develop
proof evaluation skills, in most of the
examples you
see, one or more of the rubric criteria
would
apply only in a simplistic way, if at all.
But in more complicated examples, they
will all be important.
That's why the five criteria carry equal
weights.
When you evaluate arguments, you should
view them in terms of
each of the five rubric criteria in turn,
on an equal footing.
True, experts rarely use rubrics.
They are so familiar with the proof
concept, that they
automatically and holistically judge in
terms of all those perspectives.
For a beginner, the rubric breaks up the
task of judging the overall quality of a
proof.
To judging those five aspects in turn.
Each of those five is considerably simpler
to do than the entire task.
But you still find it difficult.
After you've judged the proof in terms of
the five proof characteristics, the rubric
asks you to bring them all together to
produce a single grade for the proof.
This is the number you would enter if your
task
were to assign a single numerical grade to
someone's proof.
It corresponds to the number an expert,
working without a rubric would assign.
The rubric is designed assist you, as a
beginner, to arrive at that final grade.
Incidentally, when you're evaluating the
work of another
student, as you would in test flight if
you
do it, you do owe it to that student to be
as fair and accurate as possible.
But no one expects accuracy from someone
who's just beginning to learn about
proofs.
Because everyone's work is evaluated by
three fellow students, all anonymously
by the way, with a reported grade computed
from those three grades
plus the individual's own self grade.
It turns out that most of the time, the
final grade is pretty good.
Nevertheless, the real purpose of the test
flight evaluation process is that it
offers tremendous
benefits to the evaluator in coming to a
better appreciation of what makes a good
proof.
In simple terms, in this course, the
grading is primarily for
the benefits of the grader.