Doctor Keith Devlin is a very big
guy in the world of math education.
Not to mention the world of math research.
I'm introducing you to him here because
I love how he thinks about learning in
the world of mathematics and
how his ideas about learning relate to
learning in all sorts of topics
way outside of Mathematics.
Among many other duties, Keith is
a co-founder and Executive Director of
Stanford's Human Sciences and
Technology Advanced Research Institute,
a co-founder and president of
an educational technology company,
BrainQuake that creates
mathematical learning video games.
He's also a world economic forum fellow.
A fellow of the American Association for
the Advancement of Science.
And a fellow of
the American Mathematical Society.
Last, but definitely not least, he is
The Math Guy on National Public Radio.
Welcome Dr. Devlin.
Thanks for
being with us here today Doctor Devlin.
Let's just dive right in.
What's the biggest tip you can
share with our viewers about how to
most effectively approach a math
problem that they might be stuck on?
Well the first thing of
course is don't panic.
That's the famous Douglas Adams motto.
From the Hitchiker's Guide to The Galaxy
and it holds just as much for
mathematics as it did for,
for the Hitchiker's Guide.
You have to begin by understanding
what the problem's about.
What are you trying to do?
What do you want to achieve and
what information do you have?
You must have, I mean,
you've really gotta avoid the thing that
actually teachers try to impress on you
of trying to see if you can match it
to some template and to act quickly.
One of the worst things that I think
happens in the school system is people
come away thinking that solving math
problems is something that has to be
done at speed.
It absolutely is not.
So you have to sit back take a deep breath
begin by understanding the problem.
If the problem involves numbers
put in a few simple numbers.
Threes and fours and, and
just play with it to get a sense of it.
If it's a geometric problem do
some little diagrams or you may,
I often end up writing.
Simple little graph diagrams with dots and
lines connecting them.
Just something to give me a sense
of what that problem's about.
At that point, you can ask yourself
do I know any techniques that look as
though they would work for this problem?
If they do and
you're in luck the problem's solved.
Actually that's usually very
unsatisfying because you've just applied
somebody else's thinking.
Mathematics gets interesting when you,
you have to force yourself to find up
a new, a new method, or some new approach.
So let's just assume that none
of the techniques you know work.
The next thing is,
can I adapt an existing technique.
Well, maybe you can, maybe you can't.
If you can, that usually leaves you
with a nice feeling because
you've done something yourself.
The really challenging ones and the ones
where it gets actually exciting and fun.
Is where you,
you it's becomes clear well at least you
think that nothing you know is
going to help you with that.
At that point what you do is you,
you, you,
you basically you bash away at it several
times with, with just naive approaches.
Almost certain that it won't work.
You just try this you try that.
You, you come up with ideas based
on what the problem's asking you to
do because solving a problem is a journey.
You begin with the information you've got.
Either the information you're
given with the problem or
information you already know.
You may have to add
some extra information.
You may do a Google search find
some extra information about it.
At that point, the journey takes place and
you have to get to the goal and, and
solve the problem.
If none of the methods you try for
the first half hour, maybe I'm,
depending on the problem it could
be half hour, a couple of hours.
Sometimes it's a day or a few weeks.
But if nothing happens, then the best
thing to do is walk away from the problem.
Go and do something else.
In my case for most of my career
I was a long distance runner.
If I really came up against it.
I would put on my running gear, whatever
the weather, and I'd go out for a three or
four hour run.
And when I came back,
a I felt good I felt relaxed and
quite often on the course of that ride or,
or on that, that run or when I
got back the problem seemed different and
I could, I had some new ideas.
As I got older my knees gave away from 25
years of heavy duty running these days I
ride a bicycle.
But I'd go on my bike, and I'd go for
a three or four hour bike ride.
And I come back, and first of all, I can
approach the problem with a fresh eye.
And secondly, in some cases,
what seemed to be an impossible
problem has melted away.
I look at it and think oh,
gee, that was obvious.
Why didn't I see it before?
Well, I don't quite think
that because I know that the,
the feeling you have when you
solve a problem is always duh!
Why didn't I think of that before?
And if that doesn't work,
you start the cycle again.
You bash your way at it again, make no
progress and then you go for another
bike ride, or another swim or whatever
it is you like to do, a nice long walk.
But it's important to keep ice to keep
oscillating between bashing away at it and
then backing off and doing something
else to let the brain do it's own thing.
I think that was one of
the hardest things for
me to realize was how
important it is to back away.
That it, that sometimes especially
when it's something difficult it's as
important to be able to focus on it.
As it is to be able to
back away from it and
then come back later with a fresh
perspective and a fresh mind.
Okay, I, it, for, for difficult problems,
I have never, ever solved a difficult
problem sitting at a desk or even sitting
in my chair, thinking about the problem.
I've never done that and
I'm not sure it's possible to do that.
Because if you think about it, if a
problem's solution requires something new.
Applying all of your conscious
thinking by definition can't solve it
because you're looking for something new.
The weird thing about the brain is
when you've done that preparation of
bashing away without success and
you go and do something else.
I've mentioned physical activity because
I'm a sort of a physical active guy.
Although the biggest result in my PhD,
was actually when I was
getting out of the bath.
I, I, I'd taken a long bath, that you
don't have to sort of exert lots of
energy, you have to do
something different.
Having a bath is a,
is a famous one amongst mathematicians for
solving problems.
But somehow weird stuff happens inside the
brain when you're doing something else.
And what three hours ago seemed
like an impossible problem.
Just melts away and
everything just falls into place.
The brain sorts it out when
it's left alone to do it.
And that's exactly the kinds of ideas that
we're talking about in, in our course.
It is important to do that initial work.
It's no good just going out for
a bike ride.
You've got to have gone through that
process of really coming up against it and
seeing everything that doesn't work
because that seems to set up their mind in
order to do this mysterious stuff it does,
when you're engaged in something else.
When your conscious mind is
engaged in something else.
Absolutely.
It, that's so important.
Well, one thing that you've described,
is that, in higher mathematics.
There should be a lot less doing and
a lot more thinking.
Can you tell our viewers
what you mean by that and
how, how does that relate to areas of
learning that are outside mathematics?
Yeah and this is really where
you've got to unlearn lots of
the things that you're taught at school.
And actually you're taught, teachers do
that for very good reasons because of
the where we, especially in
the United States and parts of Europe,
the way we subject people to endless
test taking in, with timed tests.
The, the way to get through the school
system is to learn to act fast under
pressure of time and that's the last thing
you can do when it comes to mathematics.
You've really got to
let it take its course.
It's not, I mean,
people have different speeds.
I've, I've worked for
some very fast mathematicians,
the the young math professor from Stanford
who won a Field's medal recently.
She has gone on record as saying
her teachers at school thought she
wasn't good at mathematics
because she was so slow.
Well she may be slow, but she now has
the equivalent of a Nobel prize in
mathematics and, and
congratulations to her for doing that.
You really have to let it take its time.
It's a slow process.
You've gotta remember that
mathematics is relatively recent,
you know, 2 or 3,000 years.
So you're bringing what's
essentially a stone age brain
to a domain that's a couple
of thousand years old.
In fact, most mathematics
is only a few decades old.
So, how can you take this brain that,
that evolved to survive in the wilds and
to, and then more recently,
to survive in social en, environments.
How can you take that brain and apply just
all this abstract problem in mathematics?
Well the answer is we don't
really know how we do that.
What we do know is that if
you familiarize yourself with
the problem to such an extent that,
that problem is like a member of your
family then the act of solving that math
problem is actually not unlike solving
a difficult problem you have at home.
You know we're very good at
solving social problems and
problems about our environment.
Because evolution set us up for that so,
somehow we have to figure out how to
let that brain solve that abstract problem
in mathematics, and the act of getting
inside the problem and thinking about it
for a long period of time, so that it's so
familiar then the natural circuits in the
brain that serve us well all of the time.
Actually come into play for
a math problem.
Now, there, there's no proof of that, but
that's certainly my own
experience of what goes on.
Yes.
Well, all I can say is three cheers for
slow thinking and I love the idea
of thinking about math and a, and
a difficult problem as being something
that's a member of your family.
Yeah, it's you know, I mean.
Math, in many ways
mathematics problems are not,
they're not fundamentally different from
other problems except in one respect,
they're about totally abstract things.
So, someone solving a math problem has an
initial problem that someone doesn't have
if they're solving a problem in
real life or a coaching problem in,
in sort of football.
Or, or, or, or, what and
even most of the time and I,
I used to spend a lot
of time rock climbing.
And rock climbing is, is,
is partly physical but
it's also a lot of problem solving.
Because you're having to look for
these moves, you're having to
move your body in the right way.
So there's an awful lot of problem
solving that we do all of the time.
And that's what the brain evolved to do.
And in the case of mathematics, however,
the world in which you're solving those
problems isn't one we're familiar with.
You initially have to, to create that,
that world in, inside of you, and this,
I think, is why I think it's essential to
knock away at the problem for, for 10,
15 minutes, a day, two days before
you let the brain do its own thing.
My guess and my perception of what's
going on is that, that process is
making my mind familiar with that domain
with that problem to such an extent that,
that problem is just like
a problem I'd have with my family.
Or, or, or, or my workplace or whatever.
I've got all of this apparatus for solving
real world problems and social problems.
And once that math problem is inside my
mind, it's another problem just like that.
So solving the math problem
usually isn't the hard part.
The hard part is getting that
problem familiar inside your mind.
And the only way to do that is
just keep living in the problem.
Get inside the problem.
Really.
Live inside that problem for ten minutes,
half an hour, maybe even a few days.
In the case of Andrew Wile, solving
Fermat's last theorem a few years ago.
It took him seven years to
really get inside that problem,
to the point where we
could see the solution.
We'll part of what you do when your
spending a lot of time with a problem is
you're in some sense reaffying and
growing the neural structures that
are related to what you're
trying to think about.
And one of the things that Doctor Synoski
and I emphasized quite strongly in our
course is how exercise
helps actually build neural
structures it, it allows you to learn
better it allows you mem, remember better.
So how, how does exercise play a role
in your own ability to do mathematics?
That's that's a good one.
But it certainly is the case for
me if, when I was a PhD student, and
my closest colleague was a, was a,
was a, a mathematician from from
the United States, came over to England
when I was a student back in Bristol.
And he was a rock climber.
In fact I learned to rock climb with him.
And we used to go on these three or
four hour rock climbs and, and.
We would almost certainly
by the time we got to the,
to the top of the climb we'd done some
mathematics because you do a climb and
you get to a ledge and you're, you're
tied up and then you chat for a while.
As you're sort of belayed
onto the rock face.
And we'd talk about mathematics.
And then we'd forget the mathematics and
we'd do onto the physical
stuff of climbing.
And when you're climbing as,
as when you're bicycling very fast.
Your mind is totally focused
on that physical activity.
That's, your entire world is physical.
So you're focused on the climbing, or
you're focused on riding your bike.
And, but stuff is going on in
the background in your mind.
It's working on those things
that you've talked about.
And we'd finish a pitch, we'd put,
get ourselves back on [INAUDIBLE],
we'd talk about the problem.
And we've made progress on the problem.
So, as a graduate students,
I discovered this method of thinking,
doing, thinking, doing.
It was incredibly powerful.
You know, I can mix conjectures and,
and sort of self reflect as to why
the physical activity is important.
I mean, aspects clearly are.
You're focusing on that activity.
It's very refreshing you know, the,
we tend to think these days that
the mind is separate from the body.
I don't buy that.
It certainly isn't the case for me.
I find that if my body's tired
my mind is tired and vice versa.
They stimulate each other.
So the, you know, the mind did
evolve to help the body survive, and
I think it's, it's a mistake to try and
think of those as separate.
If you nurture the body, the mind follows.
You know, this, this goes back to the days
of having physical education in schools
and so forth, this is hardly original,
but I think we need to take it seriously.
I've never, ever,
well I have solved problems in the bath.
That's a, that's a,
that's a somewhat more relaxing case.
But even in the bath, it's simply,
you know, it's a, it's a,
it's an artificial environment
in which you're relaxed.
You're in water, you're doing things,
you're fresh, you're freed of the mind.
The mind is absolutely not
thinking about that problem.
It's doing other things.
In my case definitely the, the bath,
the bath examples not withstanding.
Physical activity plays a big role.
Exactly why, I don't know.
But I do know it works.
[LAUGH].
Well there is actually good research
evidence they're uncovering the,
the bio-physiological mechanisms
by which it does take an affect.
But I, I have to ask, with everything
that you do, do you ever catch yourself?
It's hard to believe, but
do you ever procrastinate?
And if you do,
what do you do to get yourself out of it?
[LAUGH] yeah.
Well, first of all, I do, do many things.
You know?
I've got my own
educational technology company.
I do lots of biking.
I, I run an institute at Stanford.
I do my teaching.
I do, I'm actually on Twitter a lot.
I do a whole bunch of things.
You might think I'm a multitasker.
I absolutely do not multitask.
Not least, because I know,
from the research that's
been done here at Stanford.
A lot of it by my late colleague,
Cliff Nass.
That shows that a, human beings
cannot multitask and b, the more you
think you're good at multitasking
the worse you are at doing it,
so I absolutely don't try to use
the serial processor to multitask.
What I do is I serial task.
I will work exclusively flat out for
periods of time.
Now they may only be ten minutes.
They may be half an hour.
Or they may be I mean recently I had
to develop a whole set of 75 puzzles.
A new set of puzzles for, for
my educational video game
that we launched last fall.
And we wanted to bring
out a different version.
I worked nonstop on that for four days.
I didn't do anything else other than eat,
sleep and
bicycle ride and my entire focus
everything else went to one side.
Was to get that thing done.
And four days later I had
the 75 puzzles worked and
tested and everything and
then I moved to something else.
So what I do is I worked very intensely
and very focused for periods of time.
I mean, you know, it's amazed that, that,
that friends and family are still by me
because this is very focused and
it excludes everything else.
You know must I must be really
difficult to live with at those times.
But everything gets excluded.
I focus on it.
And then I it comes an end.
Either because I finished the job or
I just get tired and
want to switch and I'm really getting,
getting frustrated with it.
Then I'll switch and do something else.
And what I've learned to do
very efficiently is switch from
one to the other.
It doesn't take me more than a few minutes
at most to switch from one to the other.
Procrastination comes from recognizing
that I need to make that switch.
I'll keep going and keep going, and
I'll think I want to do this little thing,
I want to do this little thing.
And I do find myself doing
lots of other little things.
I'll go start to read my Twitter feed and
things for
awhile, before making the switch.
So the one moment where I will
procrastinate is starting something new,
for obvious reasons.
You've been in the groove, you've been
making progress, and then it slowed down.
And you've got to get in another groove.
And, and I know that that
takes willpower and effort.
And like everybody else,
I do have a procrastination streak.
But the only time it affects
me is making that switch.
Once I've done it, I'm away in that domain
until I've either solved that issue, or
done it, or completed it.
Or got tired of it, and need a break.
And that, I found, works extremely well.
That, that's actually something
that we talk about in this course,
is just that idea of, you don't
need to use willpower all the time.
You just need to put it one little place,
wherever you need.
Where you're getting that cue.
That's where you need to
be applying willpower and
that seems to be exactly what you do.
And it's true that I'm fortunate to
have been able to carve out a career for
myself where most of the time I'm
doing stuff I really want to do.
So even though I may not want
to write that blog post.
I know at the back of my mind
that the moment I get into it and
written a fair sentences.
Writing that blog post will be the most
important, and most wonderful, and
rewarding thing in the world,
until it's finished.
But then I have to sort of stop that and
do something else.
And that's when there's these hiatus
moments when, when I procrastinate.
It's the, the, the, the switching gears to
something else that, that's, that I find,
I won't say I find it difficult,
because I've been doing it all my life.
But you do need willpower to do that.
At least I find I need willpower
to do that and if I'm not careful,
it will just fritter away with
social media or or whatever.
I, I feel the same way
in how I handle things.
One thing I, I like to do is.
I think of my life as like
this enormous funnel where
there's all these things that
are demanding to be done.
But then only one thing can go
through the funnel at a time.
And so you, you just gotta give it up and
realize one thing is all
you can be focusing on.
And if you have that approach it makes it
a little easier to realize that
you just can't do everything.
You just do as much as you reasonably.
Yeah.
I mean, I mean one thing I do,
do is when you know, I actually just
upgraded my computer system to a,
to a new Macintosh.
The first thing I did was went to the.
Into the system controls and
switched off every single alert.
I don't want visual alerts,
I don't want noise alerts,
I don't want to know if an email has come.
I don't want to know if
something's going on.
I literally switch off all the alerts
because I don't want things pushed to me.
I want to go and find out things when
I need them because the last thing I
want if I am in the middle of
working on an article say.
Is to have some little mip,
little beep going off to tell
me some emails has arrived.
I don't want to know that,
because that's a distraction.
I want to be in the world
of writing that article,
because if you take this human brain,
and you put it into a problem,
into a domain, and you set it free,
it loves what it's doing,
it doesn't want to give up, and
it sure doesn't want to be distracted.
And so, I don't destruct it.
I just let it do what it does.
Well, I, I thank you so
much, Doctor Devlin, for
sharing your wisdom with us, here today.
It's just been a great
pleasure talking with you.
And I know our viewers will really, really
learn a lot from what you had to say.
Okay, the pleasures been all mine,
absolutely.
Thanks so much.